<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>England's birth-right justified against all arbitrary usurpation, whether regall or parliamentary, or under what vizor soever. With divers queries, observations and grievances of the people, declaring this Parliaments present proceedings to be directly contrary to those fundamentall principles, whereby their actions at first were justifyable against the King, in their present illegall dealings with those that have been their best friends, advancers and preservers: and in other things of high concernment to the freedom of all the free-born people of England; by a well-wisher to the just cause for which Lieutenant Col. John Lilburne is unjustly in-prisoned in New-gate.</title>
            <author>Lilburne, John, 1614?-1657.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1645</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 134 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 26 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A88180</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L2102</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E304_17</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200315</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861117</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861117</idno>
            <idno type="VID">113245</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A88180)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 113245)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 50:E304[17])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>England's birth-right justified against all arbitrary usurpation, whether regall or parliamentary, or under what vizor soever. With divers queries, observations and grievances of the people, declaring this Parliaments present proceedings to be directly contrary to those fundamentall principles, whereby their actions at first were justifyable against the King, in their present illegall dealings with those that have been their best friends, advancers and preservers: and in other things of high concernment to the freedom of all the free-born people of England; by a well-wisher to the just cause for which Lieutenant Col. John Lilburne is unjustly in-prisoned in New-gate.</title>
                  <author>Lilburne, John, 1614?-1657.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 47, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Larner's Press at Goodman's Fields],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed Octob. 1645.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A well-wisher = John Lilburne.</note>
                  <note>Caption title, page 1.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication and press from from Wing; imprint date from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Recto of first leaf is blank; verso reads: The preamble, to all the free-borne people of England.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Supposed to be Lilburnes or some friends of his"; "London 8ber [i.e. October] 10th 1645".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Levellers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="preamble">
            <pb facs="tcp:113245:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:113245:2"/>
            <head>The PREAMBLE, to all the Free-borne People of <hi>ENGLAND.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Rethren</hi> and <hi>Fellow-Commons;</hi> God and the world knowes, that the well-affected party of this Kingdome (diſcerned by their voluntary aide to the Parliament) having tryed all poſſible and fair means, as much as any People for number and power of any Kingdom or Nation ever did, by Prayers, Aſſiſtance, Concurrence, Attendance, Petitions, Oblations, Informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and Diſcoveries, as well of Treaſons, as of utter deſolations, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving themſelves now at laſt to be in a far worſe condition, both in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber and power (their Lives and Eſtates, yea and precious time alſo being ſo far ſpent) then they were at the firſt; and beſides, like to looſe all, and ſcarce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to have (or leave) ſo much as their Lives, Lawes, or Liberties for a prey.</p>
            <p>And ſeeing, by manifold examples of grievous experience, that neither Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions can be eaſily accepted, juſtice truely adminiſtred, the Preſſes equally opened, the cryes of the poor heard, the teares of the oppreſſed conſidered, the ſighes of the Priſoners regarded, the miſeries of the widow and Father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe pittyed, nor ſcarcely any that are in diſtreſſe relieved but Lawes any way wreſted, moſt of our freedoms reſtrained, Ordinances, Proteſtations, Oathes, and Covenants ſlighted, the hearts of all Eſtates, King, Parliament, Prieſt and People obdured, the wicked for the moſt part abſolved, the juſt often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times condemned, and moſt of all in Authority perjured, not only by brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king that ſolemne Oath, which themſelves did make, and compelling others to take, but nevertheleſſe, by perſecuting thoſe who make Conſcience to keep it, even becauſe they will not break it. In deep, ſad, ſerious, and lamentable conſideration of all theſe grievous proceedings, and as much by feeling the ſmart, as hearing, ſeeing or knowing the verity thereof, chiefly the Opreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, taxations, Inſurrections, Rebellions, Preſecutions, Violences, Robbeies, Sequeſtrations, and Combuſtions, I with my poor one <hi>Talent,</hi> in ſtead of him that hath Ten, out of a dutifull and conſciencious love, tender and pittifull reſpect to my Nation, now in this her great defection, and apparent deſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, chiefly for the remnant thereof (who mourn in ſecret, both for her great abominations, ſins, deſolations, and their own particular tranſgreſſions, and who doubtleſſe are marked to eſcape the fury of Gods fearfull indignation;)</p>
            <p>Have uſed my beſt endeavours here, both to ſhew the maladies and reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of this ſick, ſwouning, bleeding, and dying Nation, that if God hath not ordained it, like <hi>Babell,</hi> to ſudden, inevitable and utter deſtruction, it may yet be cured, and a remnant reſerved, according to the Lords uſuall dealing in all his viſitations, remembring his tender compaſſions and mercy, even in the midſt of his moſt fearfull judgements and ſeveritie, that in deſpight of Sathan and all his inſtruments, they may doe juſtice and judgement, and praiſe him in ſincerity.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewell.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:113245:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>ENGLANDS BIRTH-RIGHT</hi> Juſtified <hi>Againſt all Arbitrary <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpation, whether</hi> REGALL <hi>or</hi> PAR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIAMENTARY, <hi>or under what Vizor ſoever.</hi> With divers <hi>Queries, Obſervations</hi> and <hi>Grievances</hi> of the People, declaring this Parliaments preſent Proceedings to be directly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to thoſe fundamentall Principles, whereby their Actions at firſt were juſtifyable againſt the <hi>King,</hi> in their preſent Illegall dealings with thoſe that have been their beſt Friends, Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancers and Preſervers: And in other things of high concernment to the <hi>Freedom</hi> of all the <hi>Free-born People</hi> of <hi>England;</hi> By a Well-wiſher to the juſt cauſe for which Lieutenant Col. <hi>JOHN LILB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RNE</hi> is unjuſtly impriſoned in <hi>New-gate.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>In the 150. <hi>page</hi> of the Booke called, An exact Collection of the <hi>Parliaments</hi> Remonſtrances, Declarations, &amp;c. publiſhed by ſpeciall Order of the Houſe of <hi>Commons,</hi> March 24. 1642. we find there a Queſtion anſwered, fit for all men to take notice of in theſe ſad times; which followeth.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
               </label>
               <hi>NOw in our extreame diſtractions, when forraigne for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces threaten, and probably are invited, and a malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant and Popiſh party at home offended, The Devill hath caſt a bone, and rais'd a Conteſtation between the KING and PARLIAMENT touching the</hi> MILITIA. <hi>His Majeſtie claims the diſpoſing of it to be in Him by the right of Law; The</hi> Parliament <hi>ſaith,</hi> Rebus ſic ſtantibus, <hi>and</hi> nolenti Rege, <hi>the Ordering of it is in them?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> 
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hich Queſtion, may receive its ſolution hy this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction. That there is in Laws an equitable, and a literall ſenſe. His Majeſtie (let it be granted) is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted by Law with the <hi>Militia,</hi> but it is for the good and preſervation of the Republick<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> againſt Forraign Invaſions or domeſtick Rebellions. For it cannot be ſuppoſed that the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> would ever by Law intruſt the King with the <hi>Militia</hi> againſt themſelves, or the Common-wealth, that intruſts them to provide for their weal, not for their woe. So that when there is certaine ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:113245:3"/>
or grounded ſuſpition, that the Letter of the Law ſhall be improved againſt the <hi>equitie</hi> of it (that is, the publick good, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the body reall or repreſentative) then the Commander going againſt its <hi>equity,</hi> gives liberty to the Commanded to refuſe <hi>obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> to the Letter: for the Law taken abſtract from its originall rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and end, is made a ſhell without a kernell, a ſhadow without a ſubſtance, and a body without a ſoul. It is the execution of Laws according to their <hi>equity</hi> and <hi>reaſon,</hi> which (as I may ſay) is the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit that gives life to Authority the Letter kills.</p>
            <p>Nor need this <hi>equity</hi> be expreſſed in the Law, being ſo naturally implyed and ſuppoſed in all Laws that are not meerly Imperiall, from that Analogie which all bodies Politick hold with the Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall; whence all Government and Governours borrow a proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onable reſpect; And therefore when the <hi>Militia</hi> of an Army is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the Generall, it is not with any expreſſe condition, that he ſhall not turn the mouthes of his Cannons againſt his own Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, for that is ſo naturally and neceſſarily implyed, that its need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe to be expreſſed, inſomuch as if he did attempt or command ſuch a thing againſt the nature of his truſt and place, it did <hi>ipſo facto</hi> eſtate the Army in a right of Diſobedience, except we think that obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience binds Men to cut their owne throats, or at leaſt their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions.</p>
            <p>And indeed, if this diſtinction be not allowed, then the legall and mixt <hi>Monarchy</hi> is the greateſt <hi>Tyranny;</hi> for if Laws inveſt the King in an abſolute power, and the Letter be not controlled by the equity, then whereas other Kings that are abſolute <hi>Monarchs,</hi> and rule by Will and not by Law, are <hi>Tyrants</hi> perforce. Thoſe that rule by Law, and not by Will, have hereby a <hi>Tyranny</hi> confer'd upon them legally, and ſo the very end of Laws, which is to give bounds and limits to the exorbitant wills of Princes, is by the laws themſelves diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, for they hereby give corroboration (and much more juſtification) to an arbitrary <hi>Tyranny,</hi> by making it legall, not aſſumed; which Laws are ordained to croſſe, not countenance: and therefore is the Letter (where it ſeems abſolute) alwayes to receive qualification from the equity, elſe the foreſaid abſurdity muſt follow. <hi>So farre the Parliaments own words.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is confeſſed by all rationall men, that the <hi>Parliament</hi> hath a po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer to annull a Law, and to make a new Law, and to declare a Law,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:113245:3"/>
but known Laws in force &amp; unrepealed by them, are a Rule (ſo long as they ſo remain) for all the <hi>Commons</hi> of <hi>England</hi> whereby to walk; and upon rationall grounds is conceived to be binding to the very <hi>Parliament</hi> themſelves as well as others. And though by their legiſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive power they have Authority to make new Laws, yet no free-man of <hi>England</hi> is to take notice (or can he) of what they intend till they declare it: neither can they, as is conceived, juſtly puniſh any man for walking cloſely to the knowne and declared Law, though it croſſe ſome pretended Priviledge of theirs, remaining onely in their own breaſts.</p>
            <p>For where there is no Law declared, there can be no tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; therefore it is very requiſite, that the <hi>Parliament</hi> would declare their Priviledges to the whole <hi>Commons</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> that ſo no man may through ignorance (by the <hi>Parliaments</hi> default) run cauſeleſly into the hazard of the loſſe of their lives, liberties, or eſtates: for here it is acknowledged by themſelves, that their Power is limited by thoſe that betruſt them; and that they are not to doe what they liſt, but what they ought, namely to provide for the peoples weal, and not for their woe: ſo that unknown Priviledges are as danger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, as unlimited Prerogatives, being both of them ſecret ſnares, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially for the beſt affected people.</p>
            <p>It is the greateſt hazard and danger that can be run unto, to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſart the onely known and declared Rule; the laying aſide whereof brings in nothing but Will and Power, luſt and ſtrength, and ſo the ſtrongeſt to carry all away; for it is the known, eſtabliſhed, declared, and unrepealed Law, that tells all the Free-men of <hi>England,</hi> that the Knights &amp; Burgeſſes choſen according to Law, and ſent to make up the <hi>Parliament,</hi> are thoſe that all the <hi>Commons</hi> of <hi>England</hi> (who ſend and chooſe them) are to obey.</p>
            <p>But take away this declared Law: and where will you find the rule of Obedience? and if there be no rule of Obedience, then it muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily follow, that if a greater and ſtronger number come to a <hi>Parliament</hi> ſitting, and tell them that they are more and ſtronger then themſelves, and therefore they ſhall not make Laws for them, but they will rather make Laws for them, muſt they not needs give place? undoubtedly they muſt.</p>
            <p>Yea<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> take away the declared, unrepealed Law, and then where is <hi>Meum &amp; Tuum,</hi> and Libertie, and Propertie? But you will ſay, the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:113245:4"/>
Law declared, binds the People, but is no rule for a Parliament ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, who are not to walke by a knowne Law. It is anſwered: <hi>It cannot be imagined that ever the People would be ſo ſottiſh, as to give ſuch a Power to thoſe whom they chooſe for their Servants;</hi> for this were to give them a Power to provide for their woe, but not for their weal, which is contrary to their own foregoing Maxime; therefore doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe that man is upon the moſt ſolid and firm ground, that hath both the Letter and <hi>equity</hi> of a known, declared, and unrepealed Law on his ſide, though his practiſe doe croſſe ſome pretended Priviledge of <hi>Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And whereas by an Act made this preſent <hi>Parliament, Anno</hi> 17. <hi>Caroli Regis,</hi> intituled,</p>
            <p>An Act for Regulating of the <hi>Privie Counſell,</hi> and for taking away the Court, commonly called, <hi>The Star-Chamber.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is there declared, That the Proceedings, Cenſures and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees of the Star-Chamber, have by experience been found to be an intollerable burthen to the Subject, and the means to introduce an Arbitrary Power and Government, and that the Councell-Table have adventured to determin of the Eſtates, and Liberties of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, contrary to the Law of the Land, and the Rights and Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges of the Subject. Which Laws are there recited, as firſt <hi>Magna Carta,</hi> and the 5. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. 9. and 25. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. 4. and 28. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. 3. the laſt of which ſaith, That it is accorded, aſſented, and eſtabliſhed, that none ſhall be taken by Petition, or ſuggeſtion made to the King or His Councell, unleſſe it be by Indictment, or preſentment of good and lawfull people of the ſame neighbourhood, where ſuch deeds be done; in due manner, or by Proceſſe made by Writ originall at the Common Law, and that none be put out of his franchiſe or Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, unleſſe he be duly brought in, to anſwer, and fore-judged of the ſame by the courſe of the Law; and by another Statute made in the 42 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. 3. it is there inacted, That no man be put to anſwer without preſentment before Juſtices, or matter of Record, or by due Proceſſe and Writ originall, according to the old Law of the Land.</p>
            <p>Therefore for the Subjects good and welfare in future time, it is Inacted, That from henceforth no Court, Councell, or place of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicature ſhall be erected, ordained, conſtituted, or appointed within this Realme of <hi>England,</hi> or dominion of <hi>Wales,</hi> which ſhall have, uſe,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:113245:4"/>
or exerciſe the ſame, or the like juriſdiction, as is, or hath been uſed, practiſed, or exerciſed in the ſaid Court of Star-Chamber; that then whoſoever ſhall offend, or doe any thing contrary to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, true intent and meaning of this Law, then he or they ſhall for ſuch offence, forfeit the Sum of five hundred pounds of Lawfull mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney of <hi>England,</hi> unto any party grieved, his Executors or Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrators, who ſhall really proſecute the ſame, and firſt obtaine judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereupon, to be recorded in any Court of Record at <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter,</hi> by Action of debt, Bill, Plaint or Information, wherein no Eſſoine, Protection, wager of Law, aid, Prayer, Priveledge, Injuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or Order of Reſtraint ſhall be in any wayes prayed, granted, or allowed, nor any more then one imparlance, &amp;c. And the <hi>Petition of Right,</hi> which may be ſaid to be more then a bare Law (for it is a Declaration of the <hi>equity,</hi> true intent and meaning of <hi>Magna Carta,</hi>) and other the good Laws of the Land, which provides for the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples freedome (and binds all, as well the truſted, as thoſe that truſt) as appeares in the Parliaments Prayer to the King, which is, That no Free-man hereafter be uſed contrary to what is before expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, &amp;c. which they ſay is the Rights and liberties of the Free-men of <hi>England,</hi> unto which the King anſweres, <hi>Let Right be done accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Lawes and Cuſtomes of the Realme;</hi> But this Anſwer ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting ſtill a Diſpute what was the true intent and meaning of the <hi>Lawes</hi> and <hi>Cuſtomes</hi> of the Realm.</p>
            <p>They Petition the King again to give a more full &amp; ſatisfactory an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, which he doth, and ſaith, <hi>Let Right be done, as in the Petition is deſired;</hi> and amongſt other things there expreſſed, it is declared to be contrary to law, to impriſon a man without cauſe ſhewed or expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and alſo that it is contrary to <hi>Law,</hi> to force a man to anſwer to Queſtions concerning himſelf, or for refuſall, to commit him to pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. <hi>So far their own words:</hi> And therefore it were well that both Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament-Committees, and all County-Committees, and other Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates in this Kingdom would compound with all thoſe honeſt and Free-men that they have at their own Wills unjuſtly committed to Priſon contrary to the true meaning of this <hi>Law,</hi> before by the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of the <hi>Law</hi> they be forced to pay 500<abbr>l.</abbr> to every man they have ſo unjuſtly Impriſoned.</p>
            <p>From the <hi>equity</hi> and letter of which <hi>Lawes,</hi> It is deſired that our learned Lawyers would Anſwer theſe inſuing QUERIES.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:113245:5"/>1. <hi>Whether the Letter and</hi> equity <hi>of this Law doe not binde the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Parliament themſelves, during the time of their ſitting, in the like caſes here expreſſed, to the ſame Rules here laid downe? Which if it ſhould be denied,</hi> Then</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Whether the Parliament it ſelf, when it is ſitting, be not bound to the obſervation of the Letter and</hi> equity <hi>of this Law, when they have to doe with Free-men, that in all their actions and expreſſions have decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red faithfulneſſe to the Common-wealth? And if this be denied;</hi> Then</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Whether ever God made any man law-leſſe? Or whether ever the Common-wealth, when they chooſe the Parliament, gave them a lawleſſe unlimmitted Power, and at their pleaſure to walke contrary to their own Laws and Ordinances before they have repealed them?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Whether it be according to Law, Juſtice, or Equity, for the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament to Impriſon or puniſh a man for d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing what they command him, and by Oath injoyne him?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Whether it be legall, juſt or equall, that when Free-men doe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour according to their duty Oath, and Proteſtation, to give in In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation to the Parliament of Treaſon acted and done by Sir</hi> John Lenthall, <hi>againſt the State and Kingdome, and long ſince communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to ſeveral Members of the Houſe of</hi> Common<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>but by them concealed and ſmothered; and now by Gods Providence brought upon the ſtage a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, and during the time that Inquiſition is made of it before the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee of Examination, before any legall charge be fixed upon Sir</hi> John Lenthall, <hi>or be required to make any Anſwer or Defence, that he ſhall be preſent to out-face, diſcourage, and abuſe the Informers and Witneſſes in the face of the Committee, without any check or controll from them?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And ſometimes, while they are ſitting about the Examination of his Treaſon, that he ſhall ſit down beſide them with his hat on, as if he were one of them, and that he ſhall injoy from the Committee ten times more fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour and reſpect, then the juſt, honeſt, and legall Informers againſt him; who by ſome of the Committees themſelves, while they are ſitting, are threatned, jeared, nick-named, and otherwayes moſt ſhamefully a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Yea, and the friends of the Informers for the State are kept without doores, and the friends of the accuſed admitted to come in alwayes with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out controll, and during the Examination of the Information, that the Committee ſhall refuſe to remove the Informers out of Sir</hi> John Len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thalls <hi>cuſtody of</hi> Kings-bench, <hi>to another Priſon, although they have been
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:113245:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
truly informed, that he hath ſet Inſtruments on work to murther them, and alſo importuned to remove them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>Whether it be nor moſt agreeable to Law, Juſtice and Equity, that ſeeing Sir</hi> John Lenthall, <hi>having ſo many friends in the Houſe concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the buſineſe, that he ſhould not rather be tried by the ſame Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of Warre in</hi> London, <hi>where Sir</hi> John Hotham <hi>and his Sonne were, then at the Parliament, his principall crime being againſt the Law Marſhall, as theirs was?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>Whether to anſwer to an Indictment, when a man is demanded Guilty or not Guilty, be not a criminall Interrogatory, concerning a mans ſelfe, and ſo a man not by law bound to Anſwer to it, eſpecially ſeeing to a Conſciencious man, who dare not lie, it is a great ſnare, who if he be indicted of a thing he hath done or ſpoken, dare not plead, Not Guilty, for feare of lying, and if he plead guilty, he ſhall become a ſelf-deſtroyer (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the law of Nature, which teacheth a man to preſerve, but not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy himſelf) in declaring that which peradventure all his Adverſaries would never be able to prove againſt him.</hi> And</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Whether it be not more ſuitable and agreeable to the true intent of</hi> Magna Carta (<hi>expreſſed in the</hi> 28. <hi>Chap. thereof) where it is ſaid,</hi> No Bailiffe from henceforth ſhall put any man to his open Law, nor to an Oath upon his owne bare ſaying, without faithfull Witneſſes brought in for the ſame, and to the true intent and meaning of the <hi>Petition of Right,</hi> and the Act made this preſent <hi>Parliament</hi> for the aboliſhing the <hi>Star-Chamber, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>For a free-man to have a charge laid againſt him, and his Adverſaries brought face to face to prove it, and then the Accuſed to have liberty to make the beſt defence for himſelf he can, which was the practiſe amongſt the very Heathen</hi> Romans, <hi>who had no light but the light of Nature to guide them,</hi> Act. 25.16.</p>
            <p>Yea, Chriſt himſelf, when his enemies endeavoured to catch him by <hi>Interrogatories,</hi> he puts them off, without an Anſwer. <hi>Luke</hi> 22.67, 68.70. <hi>Chap.</hi> 23.3.</p>
            <p>Yea, when the High <hi>Prieſt</hi> asked him about his Diſciples, and his Doctrine, He anſwers, <hi>Hee ever taught openly,</hi> and therefore ſaith he, <hi>Why aske ye mee? aske them that heard me, for they know what I ſaid,</hi> John 18.20, 21.</p>
            <p>Hence juſtly it is conceived, that the <hi>Parliament</hi> may not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne that man for contemning their Authoritie, who refuſeth to
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:113245:6"/>
anſwer to Interrogatories before them (the ſupreame Court,) who anſwereth to Interrogatories in the like caſe before an inferiour Court, but you will ſay, it is the uſuall practiſe of the COM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MON-LAW, the Queſtion is, whether that practiſe be juſt or no? or whether any Law in practiſe in the KINGDOME of <hi>England</hi> doth binde the Free-men thereof, but what is made and declared by Common Conſent in Parliament? and whether or no is there, or ought there not to be a plaine platforme agreed on, and laid down by the Parliament concerning things of ſo high con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence to all the Commons of <hi>England?</hi> and ſeeing the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment hath taken care that the <hi>Bible</hi> ſhall be in Engliſh, that ſo <hi>Lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> (as they call them) may read it as well as the Clergy, ought they not alſo to be as carefull, that all the binding Lawes in <hi>England</hi> be in Engliſh likewiſe, that ſo every Free-man may reade it as well as Lawyers (ſeeing they have <hi>Lives, Liberties</hi> and <hi>Eſtates</hi> as well as the other) and peaceably enjoy them no longer then they continue in the obſervation of the <hi>Laws</hi> of this Kingdom; whereof they are Members: and ſeeing the Lawyers are ſo full of broyles and contentions, and grow ſo rich and great thereby; have not the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple cauſe to beleeve they drive on an Intereſt of their owne, diſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrive to the Peoples well-fare; yea juggle, and put falſe gloſſes upon the <hi>Law</hi> (meerly) for their own ends: Seeing ſo great a part of it is in an unknown tongue, (which the Commons call <hi>Pedlers-french,</hi> or <hi>Heathen-Greeke,</hi>) even as our State Clergy did in the daies of old, before the Scripture was tollerated to be in Engliſh, in which dayes they could eaſily make the poor people beleeve the Poopes unwrit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten verities were as binding as Scripture Rules, which the <hi>Lawyers</hi> have given the Commons juſt cauſe to fear, is their preſent practiſe with law Caſes; many of which are beſides the Rule of the Statute-law, and alſo againſt Juſtice, Equity and Conſcience, tending to no other end, but to inſlave the People?</p>
            <p n="8">8. <hi>Whether it be not juſt and equall, that ſeeing</hi> Monopoliſers <hi>were thrown out of the Houſe about Foure yeeres agoe, as infringers upon the Common-right of all the free-men of</hi> England, <hi>in ſetting up Pattents of</hi> Soape, Salt, Lether, &amp;c. <hi>why ſhould not thoſe be partakers of the ſame juſtice now, that have been chief ſticklers in ſetting up greater Paten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tees then ever the former were?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As firſt the Patent of ingroſſing the Preaching of the Word only
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:113245:6"/>
to ſuch men as weare Black and rough garments <hi>to deceive, Zech.</hi> 13.4. and have had a Cannonicall Ordination from the Biſhops, and ſo from the Pope, and conſequently from the Divell, although the Spirit of God doth command every man that hath received a gift, <hi>to miniſter the ſame one to another, as good Stewards of the manifold grace of God,</hi> 1 Pet. 4.10, 11.</p>
            <p>And although ignorance and blindneſſe be ſo univerſall all over the Kingdome, experience teaching, that where that moſt abounds they draw their ſwords ſooneſt againſt the Parliament and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth (and ſo conſequently againſt themſelves, and continue the longeſt in their Rebellion, as now wee have woefull experience, yet theſe grand Monopolizers will neither goe amongſt them them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, nor ſuffer others without ſevere puniſhment to inſtruct and teach them the Principles of Chriſtianity, or Morallity, by means of which they become deſtroyers and murderers of ſoules and bodies, and enemies to the very Civill ſocieties of Mankind.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Monopoly is the Patent of <hi>Merchant Adventurers,</hi> who have ingroſſed into their hands the ſole trade of all woollen Commodities that are to be ſent into the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> the miſchie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouſneſſe you may at large read in a late diſcourſe conſiſting of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives for the inlargement and freedome of trade, eſpecially that of Cloath, and other wollen manufactures ingroſſed at preſent contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the law of Nature, the law of Nations, and the lawes of this Kingdome, by a company of private men, who ſtile themſelves <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant Adventurers,</hi> the firſt part of which Diſcourſe (the ſecond be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not yet come out) are to be ſold by <hi>Stephen Bowsell</hi> in <hi>Popes-head-alley.</hi> Wool being the ſtapell Commoditie of the Kingdome, and freee by the lawes and Conſtitutions of the land, for all the Free-men of <hi>England</hi> to trade in. 12. <hi>H.</hi> 6. 6. and 21. 13. the injoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of which is ſo eſſentiall a Priviledge to all the Commons of <hi>England,</hi> that whoſoever gives it from them, and by any pretended Patent or Authority whatſoever, aſſumes it to themſelves, are cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of the greateſt of puniſhments whatſoever, as thoſe that are guilty of Robbing the Free men of <hi>England,</hi> of their birth-right and Inheritance, and yet the preſent <hi>Farmers of the Cuſtome Houſe,</hi> and their Aſſociates are guilty of this capital crime, for if <hi>Naboath</hi> would not part with his Vineyard (which was his Inheritance) to the King, although he would have given him as much money as it
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:113245:7"/>
was worth, or a better for it, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 21.2. there is no reaſon why the free men of <hi>England</hi> ſhould have ſo great a part of their <hi>Birth-right,</hi> as this is, taken from them by force and violence, whether they will or no, as their multitude of Petitions to the Parliament yet unanſwered, doe declare.</p>
            <p>The third <hi>Monopoly,</hi> is that inſufferable, unjuſt and tyrannical Monopoly of Printing, whereby a great company of the very ſame Malignant fellows that <hi>Canterbury</hi> and his Malignant party en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged in their Arbitrary <hi>Deſignes,</hi> againſt both the Peoples and <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments</hi> juſt Priviledges (who turning with every winde, doe endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour by all poſſible means, as well now as then, to ſell and betray the Kingdome for their own gaine,) are inveſted with an Arbitra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry unlimmitted <hi>Power,</hi> even by a generall Ordinance of Parliament, to print, divulge and diſperſe whatſoever Books, Pamphlets and Libells they pleaſe, though they be full of <hi>Lyes,</hi> and tend to the poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning of the Kingdom with unjuſt and Tyrannicall <hi>Principles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And not only ſo, but moſt violently (even now in Parliament time, which ſhould be like a cryed <hi>Faire,</hi> and each one free to make the beſt uſe of their <hi>Ware,</hi> both for the bublick, and their own pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate good) to ſuppreſſe every thing which hath any true Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the juſt Rights and Liberties of the free-borne people of this Nation<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and to brand and traduce all ſuch Writers and Writings with the odious termes of Sedition, Conſpiracie and Treaſon, but to countenance and authorize ſuch as ſhall calumniate them, and ſo both accept &amp; reward ſuch men far better then their moſt faithfull ſervants and beſt advancers, juſt as the Biſhops formerly did againſt both the <hi>Scots,</hi> and the Parliament themſelves.</p>
            <p>They doe not reſt here neither, but are yet further authorized with a generall Ordinance of this very Parliament, contrary to all law, juſtice, equity and reaſon, under pretence of ſearching for ſcandalous Books, to call numbers of deboyſt men with Smiths and Conſtables, yea and the trained Bands alſo (when they pleaſe) to aſſiſt them, and in moſt bold and tumultuous manner to break open and rifle, even the Parliaments owne (in all their greateſt dangers, troubles &amp; diſtreſſes) moſt faithfull friends Houſes, Cheſts, Truncks and Drawers; and from thence to rob, ſteale, and felloniouſly to carry away ſuch of the Poſſeſſors proper goods, choice Linnens, and beſt things, as they pleaſe, as well as Books new and old, after they
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:113245:7"/>
have put the owners themſelves out of doores, and commanded Conſtables to carry them before a Committee, and from thence to Priſon.</p>
            <p>Where they may without any conſideration rott, if they will not either betray both a good Cauſe, and ſome other of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments beſt friends, when they had few others, or elſe ſubmit to their unjuſt lawes; beſides, it is a common thing for ſuch lawleſſe men to breake in, and ſearch honeſt mens ſhops, when neither the owners nor any of theirs are preſent to ſee what buſineſſe they have there.</p>
            <p>And yet as unjuſtly as all the reſt, they doe not onely allow the weekly printing, divulging and diſperſing of <hi>Oxford Aulicus,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Malignant Books and Pamphlets, tending to the ruine both of the <hi>Kingdome</hi> and <hi>Parliaments Priviledges,</hi> but likewiſe the ſending of Printing matterialls to the King, whereby to Print down both Power of Parliament, and freedome of People.</p>
            <p>All which unjuſt dealings doe come to paſſe alſo with the privity of the Maſters and Wardens of the <hi>Stationers</hi> Company, as was o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly proved to their faces at their publick Hall; who therefore like wiſe men perceiving the Plague afarre off, would not goe on ſtill and be puniſhed, but moſt cunningly, both to hide themſelves, and their treachery againſt the well-affected party, and divide their ſpoile, ſo unjuſtly obtained by lying in waite for blood, they have now procured by this their good ſervice to the Parliament (as they did to the Biſhops) the forme or power of a <hi>Stationer-Committee</hi> in <hi>London</hi> among themſelves, that they may henceforth without ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Cenſure or Reſiſtance of <hi>Higher Powers,</hi> both abſolve the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and condemne the juſt, and ſo doe whatſoever they liſt.</p>
            <p>The next <hi>Monopoly,</hi> it is to be feared will be upon <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Beere,</hi> for as juſtly may there be a Monopoly upon them, as upon the former.</p>
            <p>Oh <hi>Engliſhmen!</hi> Where is your freedoms? and what is become of your <hi>Liberties</hi> and <hi>Priviledges</hi> that you have been fighting for all this while, to the large expence of your <hi>Bloods</hi> and <hi>Eſtates,</hi> which was hoped would have procured your <hi>liberties</hi> and <hi>freedomes?</hi> but rather, as ſome great ones Order it, ties you faſter in bondage and ſlavery, then before; therefore look about you betimes, before it be too late, and give not occaſion to your Children yet unborne to
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:113245:8"/>
curſe you, for making them ſlaves by your covetouſneſſe, cowardly baſeneſſe, and faint-heartedneſſe; therefore up as one man, and in a juſt and legall way call thoſe to account, that endeavour to deſtroy you, and betray your Liberties and Freedomes.</p>
            <p n="9">9 <hi>Whether it be not more agreeable to Equitie, Law, Juſtice, and Conſcience, that the badge of a Malignant, or a man uncapable of hearing Office in the Common-wealth, or being choſen to ſit in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as one to make Laws, ſhould not rather be, for being diſaffected to common Freedome, and having either in purſe or perſon declared his diſaffection thereunto, in any ways aſſiſting the Common enemy, who hath drawne his ſword, to deſtroy the freedome of the Common-wealth, which by the Law of this Land is granted unto the Free People thereof, (by means of which all ſuch have disfranchiſed themſelves) then for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſing out of Conſcience to take the</hi> Nationall Covenant?</p>
            <p>Which was firſt ordained to beget Unity between the Nations, but as ſad experience teacheth, in its effects produceth nothing leſſe amongſt us, ſetting us at as bitter a Warre and conteſtation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt our ſelves, (almoſt as wee have with our profeſſed enemies) who before this unhappy make-baite came amongſt us, were knit together in love and affection as one man againſt the common ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of our Liberties, <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>ſafety,</hi> and had no upbraiding one another with being a <hi>Covenanter,</hi> or an <hi>Anti-Covenanter,</hi> which breeds conſtant heart-burnings amongſt us, and which if it be not by ſome wiſe, moderate and diſcreet means) prevented, is likely to burſt out into a dangerous flame in the midſt of us, ſo that our be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing knit faſter to God, and each to other by a band of Unity, is here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by fruſtrated.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the Preamble of the <hi>Covenant</hi> it ſelfe ſaith, that the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of it is not the chiefe part of it, but the keeping of it, the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits of it being ſure and ſtedfaſt to us, when wee are ſure and ſtedfaſt in the Obſervation of the things Covenanted: ſo that if there be not the Obſervation of them, the ends and intention of it is voide and fruſtrate; but it is obſerved that many of thoſe that authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed it, and firſt took it, within a little after, runne both out of the Houſe of Peeres and Commons to the King to <hi>Oxford,</hi> and drew their ſwords againſt it, to deſtroy it, and ſo became wilfully perju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and the moſt part of the reſt that ſtill remaine, have been very
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:113245:8"/>
active in ſetting up things quite contrary to the true and declared intent and meaning of the <hi>Covenant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As firſt, it tyes all thoſe that take it without reſpect of perſons, to indeavour the extirpation of Popery, but contrary hereunto there is an Ordinance lately made for the ſtrict payment of <hi>Tythes,</hi> to the <hi>Clergy,</hi> for their maintenance, although it be one of the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt branches of <hi>Popery</hi> that ever was eſtabliſhed in <hi>Rome,</hi> the taking away of which in any place where <hi>Popery</hi> is profeſſed, is a more di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect way to root up <hi>Popery,</hi> then the taking away all things elſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed by the Papiſts, for the Clergy are ſuch greedy dogges, as the Prophet calls them, that they can never have enough, <hi>being ſheep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heards that cannot underſtand, ſeeing they all look to their owne way, every one for his gaine, Eſai.</hi> 56.10, 11. that they will be of any Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion where riches or profit is to be had, and will be ſure to avoide and hate that Religion that brings in no profit to fill and cram their fat guts, <hi>who bite with their teeth, and prepare warre for thoſe that putteth not into their mouthes.</hi> Micah. 3.5. Beſides, <hi>Tythes</hi> is a Jewiſh Ceremony aboliſhed, as all the reſt by the death of Chriſt upon the Croſſe, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.5.12.28. <hi>&amp;</hi> 8.5. <hi>&amp;</hi> 9.9.15.26.28. the eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhing of which againe, <hi>is the denying of CHRIST'S death, and a ſetting up of</hi> Moſes <hi>and the Ceremoniall law:</hi> for as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.3. <hi>For I teſtifie againe to every man that is Circumciſed, that hee is a debter to doe the whole law,</hi> yea ſaith he, <hi>Chriſt is become of no ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect to ſuch a man,</hi> ſo ſay I, Hee that compells you to pay Tythes, compels you to keep the whole Law, which whoſoever goes about, is fallen from Grace. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.4. Againe, the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ent of <hi>Tythes</hi> is an unjuſt and unequall thing in a Civill ſenſe, for that the Prieſts who are not one for a thouſand of the reſt of the Inhabitants in the Kingdome ſhould have the tenth part, yea, or rather the ſeventh part of all things a man hath (ſaving his Children) conſidering that they never labour for it with their hands, nor earne it with the ſweat of their browes, nor beſtow any kind of Charges, is the moſt unjuſt thing in the world, and ſo intollerable oppreſſing a burthen, that the <hi>Free-people</hi> of <hi>England</hi> are not able to beare it, as the Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions preſented by divers perſons already to the Houſe, and thoſe many Petititions that are in agitation both in the City of <hi>London,</hi> and many Shires in the Country doe and will fully declare.</p>
            <p>A ſecond thing ſworne to in the Covenant, as other branches of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:113245:9"/>
Popery is, <hi>to root out and exterpate Prelacy</hi> (as there it is expreſſed, <hi>Church-Government by Archbiſhops, Biſhops, their Chancellors and Commiſſaries, Deanes, ſub-Deanes and Chapiters, Archdeacons, and all other Eccleſiaſticall Officers depending on that Hierarchy,</hi>) and yet the ſame men have eſtabliſhed the Biſhop's Prieſts, and ſervants, who have no other calling in the world whereby to ſtand, but what they had from them, as both the Ordinance and the Prieſts themſelves confeſſe, and yet by vertue of this Papall, Prelaticall Call, they In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute and ordaine a Generation of <hi>Antichriſtian Officers,</hi> to fill the Kingdome (contrary to the <hi>Covenant</hi>) as full of Popery and Popiſh Officers, as ever it was in the Biſhops dayes: the drivers on of which deſigne <hi>(if they have taken the Covenant,)</hi> are every man of them perjured.</p>
            <p>But you will ſay though the <hi>Parliament</hi> and <hi>Prieſts</hi> acknowledge the <hi>Biſhops</hi> to be Antichriſtian, yet the preſent <hi>Prieſts</hi> ſay, they were not ordained by them as Biſhops, but as Presbiters, who had their Calling from the Pope, not as a Pope, but as a <hi>Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which I Anſwer, the Devill was an Angel of Light, but is now a Devill; the queſtion is, Whether now hee doth thoſe actions that he doth as an <hi>Angel of Light,</hi> or as a <hi>Devill?</hi> Even ſo, (admit for Diſputations ſake only it ſhould be granted,) the <hi>Pope</hi> was once a <hi>Presbyter,</hi> but is now a <hi>Pope, Antichriſt, the man of ſinne, and ſonne of Perdition,</hi> as is confeſſed by the <hi>Prieſts</hi> themſelves, The Queſtion therefore to them is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ether the <hi>Pope</hi> doth the actions that he doth as a <hi>Presbyter,</hi> or as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd <hi>Antichriſt</hi> the Pope; againe, the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, as they themſelves confeſſe, are <hi>Antichriſtian,</hi> and as <hi>Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian</hi> hath petitioned againſt them to this very <hi>Parliament,</hi> that ſo they might be extirpated <hi>root</hi> and <hi>branch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Queſtion now to the <hi>Prieſts</hi> is, Whether the <hi>Biſhops</hi> did thoſe actions that they did after they were made <hi>Biſhops,</hi> as <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian Biſhop,</hi> or as JESUS CHRIST'S <hi>Presbyters?</hi> and if they were <hi>Antichriſtian,</hi> then ſurely thoſe that are made by them are the ſame, and not in the leaſt degree any better, for the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.7. without all contradiction, <hi>the leſſe is bleſſed of the greater,</hi> therefore for theſe men to ſay, <hi>they are better then thoſe that made them,</hi> is a meer rediculous foppery; Chriſt himſelfe telling all ſuch men, <hi>they are very fooles, Matth.</hi> 23.16, 17, 18, &amp;c. where in the like
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:113245:9"/>
caſe hee ſaith unto the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees; Woe unto you blinde guides, which ſay, Whoſoever ſhall ſware by the Temple, it is nothing, but whoſoever ſhall ſweare by the gold of the Temple, he is a debter. Yee fooles and blind: For whether is greater, the gold, or the Temple that ſanctifieth the gold? and whoſoever ſhall ſweare by the Altar, it is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but whoſoever ſweareth by the gift that is upon it, hee is guilty. Ye fooles and blind: for whether is greater, the gift, or the Altar that ſanctifieth the Gift. Whoſoever therefore ſhall ſweare by the Altar, ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth by it, and by all things thereon: and who ſhall ſweare by the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, ſweareth by it, and by him that dwelleth therein:</hi> read likewiſe the 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.17. <hi>Hoſea.</hi> 9.4.</p>
            <p>From all which places, to my underſtanding, it cleerly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares, that no man whatſoever can be inſtated into any Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice whatſoever by an <hi>Antichriſtian Power,</hi> but his <hi>Functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> is as <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> as his that made him, for as <hi>James</hi> ſaith, <hi>chap.</hi> 3.11. <hi>Doth a fountaine ſend forth at the ſame place ſweet water, and bitter?</hi> therefore in the words of the <hi>Prophet</hi> Eſai. <hi>chap.</hi> 5.20. <hi>I ſay, woe unto them that call evill good, that put darkneſſe for light, and light for darkneſſe, that put bitter for ſweet, and ſweet for bitter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if this be not enough to prove them <hi>Antichriſtian,</hi> but that yet they think the ſtream of <hi>Presbyterian</hi> impoſition of hands is run ſo cleer from the Apoſtles to the Pope, and from the Pope to the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, and from the Biſhops to them, I would faine know of them how they will be able to prove, that it purely came through the hands of <hi>Pope JOANE,</hi> or where they will ever finde in the <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> that ever a woman in their ſenſe was a <hi>Presbyter,</hi> or ever laid her hands upon other <hi>Presbyters,</hi> to ordaine them.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, How they will be able to prove their ſucceſſion to come truly to them, ſeeing there hath been ſometimes two <hi>Popes</hi> at once, and ſometimes three, and each excommunicating the other as falſe, how they will be able infalibly to make it appeare, that their <hi>Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation</hi> came from the true <hi>Pope,</hi> and not from the falſe? Or how out of the <hi>New-Teſtament</hi> they will ever be able to prove, that a Biſhop, Paſtor or Teacher, did ever lay his hands to ordaine ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Biſhop, Paſtor, or Teacher? and till they be able ſatisfactorily to anſwer to all theſe <hi>Queries,</hi> I ſhall account them as <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> as the Biſhops, and as papiſticall as the <hi>Pope</hi> himſelf, and every man a perjured man that hath taken the <hi>Covenant,</hi> that doth not earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:113245:10"/>
endeavour to extirpate and root them out, their power and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt being ſo deſtructive to the Peace, Safety and Freedome of a Nation, as all ages, times and places doe fully declare where they have had footing; and this the <hi>Parliaments</hi> owne Declaration, made the Fifteenth day of <hi>December,</hi> 1642, doth cleerly hold out, which is worth every true-hearted <hi>Engliſh-mans</hi> ſerious peruſall and Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation.</p>
            <p>In the third place, they ſweare to preſerve the Liberties of the Kingdome, and yet commit men to priſon for ſtanding for them, witneſſe Lieutenant Colonell <hi>Lilburnes</hi> lying in <hi>New-gate,</hi> commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted originally, no man knowes wherefore; and thoſe that were the Authors of his impriſonment, are aſhamed to this day to tell him for what cauſe they have committed him: And becauſe they would faine pick a hole in his coat, they not onely keep his eſtate from him, but as if they intended to deſtroy him without remedy, doe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit him to priſon, which action indeed tendeth to his utter ruine, and then lay all the Provocations and aſperſions upon him, which they can deviſe againſt him in his Impriſonment, becauſe they had none before.</p>
            <p>And then at their laſt pinch, examine him upon Interrogatories at the Committee of Examinations, concerning himſelf, (juſt <hi>High-Commiſſion</hi> and <hi>Star-Chamber-like,</hi>) and becauſe he ſtands upon his right, and the law of the Land, and will not anſwer, they turne him over to <hi>New-gate</hi> amongſt Roagues and Cut-purſes, there to brand him with infamie as much as in them lyeth, that ſo it ſhall never be taken off from him as long as he lives, and then to make Orders to arraigne him at <hi>New-gate</hi> Seſſions, if they can deviſe a crime, and get Lawyers to plead againſt him, before they have done him one bit of juſtice in helping him to the moneys they owe him.</p>
            <p>O <hi>Engliſhmen,</hi> what doe you think of the makers, and firſt takers of this Covenant, are they perjured yea or no? are you able to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcerne the benefit of forced Covenants, are they not like forced Religion?</p>
            <p>In the fourth place, they ſweare faithfully, <hi>To diſcover all ſuch as have been, or ſhall be Incendiaries, Malignants, or evill Inſtruments a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the publick good, and what miſchief they are not able in their own perſons to ſuppreſſe or overcome, that they ſhall reveale or make knowne, that it may be timely prevented or remedied;</hi> all which they ſweare to doe, as in the ſight of GOD.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:113245:10"/>And yet notwithſtanding, although Lieutenant Generall <hi>Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well,</hi> according to his duty long ſince, revealed the Earl of <hi>Manche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters</hi> treachery and baſeneſſe at <hi>Dennington</hi> Caſtle, and other places, and proved it punctually by unqueſtionable witneſſes before a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee of the Houſe of Commons, and before hee could <hi>perfect his charge,</hi> he was ſent upon an unhopefull deſigne with Sir <hi>William Waller</hi> to relieve <hi>Taunton</hi> with Horſe, although it be an exceeding cloſe incloſed Country, where a hundred foot may deale with a thouſand horſe.</p>
            <p>And when he came back to <hi>Windſor,</hi> he was poſted away <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riah-like,</hi> by ſpeciall command, with his owne Regiment of Horſe, to lie betwixt <hi>Oxford</hi> and <hi>Worceſter,</hi> (in the very roade way of deſtruction, had not the Noble Generall (by GODS Providence) exceedingly ſtrengthned his party) and after that, hee is poſted from place to place, and never ſuffered to come to the Parliament ſince, whereby <hi>Mancheſters</hi> treaſon lies, as it were hid, although it be more fully proved (as ſome of that Houſe have ſince confeſſed) then ever <hi>Strdf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fords</hi> was; and yet he is ſuffered to act in all the great deſignes of the Kingdome, unto this preſent.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Maſter <hi>Muſſenden</hi> and Mr. <hi>Wolley,</hi> and divers others (Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen of quallity) of the Committee of <hi>Lincolne,</hi> in <hi>Auguſt,</hi> 1644. exibited Articles of <hi>High-Treaſon,</hi> and other hainous miſdemeanors againſt Colonell <hi>Edward King,</hi> to the Houſe of <hi>Commons:</hi> which Articles they have ſince Printed and publiſhed to the view of the World; yet can they not to this day get any hearing of them, that ſo they may prove againſt him what they accuſe him of, howbeit, although in their Fourth and Twelfth Article, they accuſe him of plaine <hi>High-Treaſon,</hi> their owne words are as followeth: As</p>
            <p>Article 4. <hi>When hee (the ſaid Colonell</hi> King) <hi>was before</hi> Newarke, <hi>he ſent for a Captaine, who kept</hi> Crowland, <hi>who obeyed his command, yet ſent word to him of the danger that Towne was in, and therefore deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red his ſecond pleaſure, which was, That he ſhould march; who according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly did; the Gentlemen of the Country fearing the enemy, procured Major</hi> Ireton <hi>to ſend a</hi> 100. <hi>Musketiers to keep</hi> Crowland, <hi>which hee hearing of, took ill, that without Order from him, any ſhould come into his liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and commanded them to be gone, who accordingly departed; the enemy preſently ſurpriſed the Towne, and thoſe few that he had left in it, by which meanes he betrayed the Towne unto the enemy, which was not regain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:113245:11"/>
without much charge, hazard, and loſſe of many mens lives.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Article the 12. <hi>That when the Enemy took</hi> Grantham, <hi>they being beaten from one part of the Town, wheeled about, to fall upon the other ſide, at a place called</hi> Spittle-gate, <hi>which Major</hi> Savill <hi>(being then Major of the Towne) perceiving, commanded Colonell</hi> King <hi>(being then Captaine of a Company there) to march with his Company to defend that place, Colonell</hi> King <hi>anſwered, That he ſcorned to be commanded by him, and rather then he would be commanded by him, he would take his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, and let the enemy into the Towne, and he delayed ſo long before hee would goe, that the enemy was entred at the ſaid Part before hee came thither, by which means be betrayed that Towne.</hi> Alſo,</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>John Muſgrave</hi> Gentleman, hath complained to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons in this preſent Parliament againſt <hi>Richard Barwis</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr> Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſſe for <hi>Carlile,</hi> and a Member now ſitting in the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, and lately one of the Commiſſioners of Parliament for both Kingdomes, that at his being at <hi>Edenborough,</hi> he held correſponden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy with the Commiſſioners of <hi>Array,</hi> both for <hi>Weſtmerland</hi> and <hi>Cumberland,</hi> and in his Twentieth Article againſt him, he ſaith, <hi>That when the ſaid</hi> Richard Barwis <hi>was at</hi> Sunderland, <hi>hee had Intercourſe by Letters with the chief Delinquents in</hi> Cumberland, <hi>which were, eſpecially Baronet</hi> Graham, <hi>Baronet</hi> Muſgrave, <hi>Baronet</hi> Curwen, <hi>and</hi> Sir <hi>Willfrede Lawſon;</hi> and <hi>that the ſaid Mr.</hi> Barwis <hi>Eſtate was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected by means of ſome of the foreſaid Knights, during the time the King had the Command of the North, and that Mr.</hi> Barwis <hi>was an Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in getting men nominated to be Committee-men for the</hi> Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>while they were in actuall Rebellion againſt the Parliament and Kingdome, and hath been an inſtrument in getting the Command of both the foreſaid Counties into the hands of thoſe that actually have been in Armes, and committed treaſon againſt the Common-wealth, who a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe the honeſt well-affcted to the Parliament there, as much as ever they were while the King had the Command of them: and though complaint hath been made of all this to many of the Houſe of Commons, and much more by Mr.</hi> Muſgrave, <hi>and his partner, who are ſent up to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from the Country (as Commiſſioners for that purpoſe) yet they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be heard or finde any</hi> Juſtice <hi>againſt Mr.</hi> Barwis, <hi>and the other De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquents, by means whereof, both the Counties are in danger ſhortly to be loſt and deſtroyed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:113245:11"/>4. Some Gentlemen of the Biſhopricke of <hi>Durham,</hi> long ſince complained to divers Parliament men of old Sir <hi>Henry Vanes</hi> wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full looſing and betraying their Country, being there Lord Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant, but by reaſon of his greatneſſe could never be heard, but in regard the ſubſtance of his charge is come into my hands, from the hands of a Gentlemen of that Country now in <hi>London:</hi> I have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted here, that you may read it as followeth, only with this cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that ſeeing in the Copy I took it out of, there were ſome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terlynings at the latter end thereof, that if a word ſhould be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placed, you would not therefore throw aſide all the reſt of it, for I dare pawne my life, the ſubſtance of it will be proved.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Militia</hi> of the County of <hi>Durham</hi> was intruſted with Sir <hi>Henry Vane</hi> the elder, to whom ſome Gentlemen of the Country re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired, and deſired his care therein, which he omitting, the Earl of <hi>Newcaſtle</hi> in <hi>Auguſt,</hi> 1642. taking advantage thereof, came into the County of <hi>Durham,</hi> and to the Towne of <hi>Newcaſtle</hi> upon <hi>Tyne,</hi> with divers Captaines, Commanders, not exceeding the number of 100. men, to raiſe forces againſt the Parliament, and by <hi>Michaelmas</hi> after, he increaſed to 500. or 600. men at the moſt, and Sir <hi>Henry Vane</hi> having Armes of his owne in his Houſe at <hi>Rahy</hi> Caſtle, ſufficient to arme 100. men, thoſe Armes were carried by his two principall ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, <hi>William Conyers,</hi> a Popiſh Recuſant, and <hi>Henry Dingly</hi> his ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liciter in his Law affaires, to the Towne of <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> where they were delivered to one appointed by the Earle of <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive them, and <hi>Conyers</hi> and <hi>Dingley</hi> received a note for the receit of thoſe armes.</p>
            <p>All which being publikely known in the Country, the people were much diſheartned, and for that the party intruſted with the <hi>Militia,</hi> had furniſhed the enemie as aforeſaid, many were forced to take up Armes under the command of the Earle of <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> divers for feare fled out of the Country, and others of them, who ſtaid longer, were taken and impriſoned: and ſhortly after, the Earles Army increaſed to the number of 5000. and upwards, as it was commonly reputed; there being 39. Colours of foot, and 25 Troops of Horſe, or neere thereabouts; and the affected plundered in their Eſtates to their utter impoveriſhment.
<q>Our humble deſire is, That no man that hath taken up Armes, and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:113245:12"/>
ſerved, or been active in this unnaturall Warre, againſt the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or are Delinquents, or willingly contributed thereunto, be put into Commiſſion, or imployment, or Adminiſtration of Juſtice, untill the well-affected of the Country be heard concerning their offences, and miſdemeanours, and the ſame be determined of in the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, &amp;c.</q>
            </p>
            <p>This Information was preſented to the Right Honourable the Earle of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> in <hi>February,</hi> 1643. by <hi>Richard Lilburne,</hi> and his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>George Lilburne,</hi> in the preſence of <hi>Edward Wright, Nicholas Heath, John Ewbanke,</hi> and <hi>Michael Dawſon,</hi> all of the County of <hi>Durham.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="copy">
                        <head>¶ The Copies of Colonell THO. MIDFORDS Certificate, with others, given under their hands.</head>
                        <p>THat about <hi>July,</hi> 1642. <hi>Thomas Midford</hi> and <hi>George Lilburne</hi> went on purpoſe to the Houſe of Sir <hi>Henry Vane</hi> the elder, neere <hi>Charing-Croſſe,</hi> and there acquainted him of the free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent meetings of the Papiſts and their adherents, in the County of <hi>Durham,</hi> and that they did not onely gather together moſt of the prime Horſes of the ſaid County, but did exerciſe them in Armes, and trained the ſaid Horſe, to the diſcouragement of all the true-hearted Proteſtants of the ſaid County: And that the Sea-ports of the ſaid County were fit to betaken care of, which the ſaid Sir <hi>Henry Vane</hi> promiſed to take timely care of, making ſhew that hee intended ſhortly to goe downe into the ſaid County: In the meane time, deſired the ſaid <hi>George Lilburne,</hi> and the ſaid <hi>Thomas Midford</hi> to goe to the Deputy Lieutenants, and acquaint them with the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid Information, and to tell them from him, that he could not then write to them concerning the ſame, but bid them take care thereof, till he gave further Order.</p>
                        <p>The ſaid <hi>Thomas Midford,</hi> about the end of the ſaid moneth, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming into the ſaid County, went to <hi>Durham,</hi> and did acquaint Sir <hi>William Darcie,</hi> being then high Sheriffe of the ſaid County, Sir <hi>John Conyers</hi> and others at <hi>John Halls</hi> Houſe in <hi>Durham,</hi> of the ſame, who returned the ſaid <hi>Midford</hi> no other anſwer, but <hi>well, well,</hi> and ſeemed to make no great matter thereof.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <dateline>
                              <date>18 <hi>June,</hi> 1645.</date>
                           </dateline>
                           <signed>Tho. Midford.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="copy">
                        <pb n="21" facs="tcp:113245:12"/>
                        <p>In the yeere 1643, <hi>Nicolas Heath</hi> of <hi>Little-Eden</hi> in the County of <hi>Durham</hi> 
                           <abbr>Eſq</abbr> came to Sir <hi>Hen. Vane ſenior</hi> in <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall,</hi> and told him that the County was in a very ſad Condition, and the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants utterly undone, unleſſe there were ſome preſent courſe ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for preventing of raiſing the forces which were then a gathering; but Sir <hi>Henry Vanes</hi> Anſwer was, <hi>That he never thought otherwiſe.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>NIC. HEATH.</signed>
                           <dateline>
                              <date>18 <hi>June,</hi> 1645.</date>
                           </dateline>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Henry Dingly</hi> died in <hi>Jan.</hi> 1644. at <hi>Charing-Croſſe,</hi> and lodged neer Sir <hi>Henry Vanes</hi> Houſe, <hi>teſtis John Marr,</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr> Clarke of the Kitching to the Prince.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>William Conyers,</hi> Steward of his Land, hath continued in his ſervice likewiſe, and lived in <hi>Raby Caſtle,</hi> ever ſince the carrying of the Armes from the ſaid Caſtle to <hi>Newcaſtle</hi> upon <hi>Tyne,</hi> till within theſe Foure moneths laſt paſt, <hi>Teſtis,</hi> Mr. <hi>George Lilburne,</hi> and Col. <hi>Rob. Lilburne,</hi> his Nephew. <hi>June</hi> 2. 1645.</p>
            <p n="5">5. When Alderman <hi>Gurney</hi> was Lord Major of <hi>London,</hi> the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens complained to the Parliament of him and others of his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, and alſo of the Recorder <hi>Gardner,</hi> thoſe that proſecuted the Cities buſines, was principally Alderman <hi>Folkes,</hi> and Alderman <hi>Gibbs,</hi> that Monopoliſer, and Mr. <hi>Gline</hi> now Recorder, ſate in the Chaire of that Committee, but as ſoon as they had juſtled out thoſe, they complained of, and ſet themſelves downe in their pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces or Saddles, rode and ſpurr'd the poor Commons of <hi>London</hi> as hard as ever the former did, and troad in <hi>Strafford's</hi> pathes of Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Goverment, as much as the former, and the People ſigh, groane, and cry out of their unjuſt bondage by the Lord Major preſent, Recorder and Court of Aldermen, and the Parliament look upon them with a ſlighting eye, and afford them no helpe, though the Commons of <hi>London</hi> have been chief Inſtruments under GOD of ſaving their Lives, Liberties, and Eſtates, howbeit now they goe about to make them ſlaves for their paines; it were well therefore the <hi>Commons</hi> of <hi>London</hi> would aske their <hi>Foure Burgeſſes,</hi> if they did not ſend them to ſit in Parliament, to preſerve and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend their Liberties, and if they finde they have not performed their truſt, then to deſire to chooſe Foure more Faithfull, Carefull and ſtouter in their places, and that the Commons of <hi>London</hi> are ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of their being rob'd of their Freedomes by the aforeſaid par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:113245:13"/>
the Petition of divers of them preſented to the whole Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Councell, ſitting in <hi>Guild-hall</hi> in <hi>Aprill</hi> laſt, and ſince printed, doth fully declare; whereof a true Copy here followeth.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="petition">
                        <head>To the Right Honourable, The LORD MAJOR, and the Right Worſhipfull, the <hi>Aldermen,</hi> and <hi>Common-Councell of the City</hi> of LONDON; <hi>In Common Councell Aſſembled.</hi> The humble Petition of divers Citizens of this Honourable City.</head>
                        <opener>SHEWING,</opener>
                        <p>THat the afflictions and ſorrows of our hearts are unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſable in regard of the manifold miſeries that are upon us, and thouſands of our deer Brethren, and fellow Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens, complaints being generall, and very grievous. As amongſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other;</p>
                        <p n="1">I. <hi>That the Poore is in great neceſſity, wanting wherewith to ſet themſelves on worke, their Children uneducated, and thereby prepared, to wickedneſſe and beggery.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="2">II. <hi>That Trading is exceedingly decayed, whereby thouſands that have lived in a free and plentifull way, are many fallen, and are more fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling into great extremity.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="3">III. <hi>That Aſſeſments are made very unequall, whereby the Taxes laid upon the City, are made burthenſome, and paid with much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pining.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="4">IV. <hi>That the Forces of the Citie are very much abated, and that the Citie is not in a Poſture of Warre anſwerable to its greatneſſe, or its danger.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>And though there hath not been wanting continuall endeavours of juditious charitable perſons to preſcribe remedies for thoſe grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances, yet our miſeries are ſuch, that we are in effect debarred from opening our griefes, or propoſing our remedies to any that hath power to help us.</p>
                        <p>For if wee motion our going to the Parliament immediately (as
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:113245:13"/>
was uſuall and ſucceſsfull in former times) our mouthes are preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtopt with this prejuditiall rumour. <hi>That the Parliament will not receive any Petition from the Citizens, but by the Common-Councell;</hi> whereupon few or none will move in that way, though there be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo urgent neceſſities.</p>
                        <p>If wee propoſe to goe through the <hi>Common-Councell,</hi> ſad experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence hath proved it ſo difficult to obtaine a Common-Councell, that men are weary in purſuance thereof. The Lord Major and Aldermen challenging to themſelves Prerogative of calling Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Councells onely when (they ſee cauſe,) alſo that nothing ſhall be debated, but what hath been firſt preſented to the Court of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermen, and that after debate, the Lord Major hath a negative voice or power to Null or fruſtrate all that hath been debated by refuſing to put to Vote, or by diſſolving the Court at his pleaſure. By which Prerogative Rules, if the Lord Major will not, or cannot preſerve the Citizens from miſeries and deſtruction, Will not heare our Complaints, nor be ſenſible of our neceſſities, The whole power of the choſen Common-Councell men, may not interpoſe, or uſe any meanes for our preſervation and relief. Wee willingly give all due honour to the Lord Major and Aldermen in referrence to their particular Offices. But that the ſafety and well-being of ſo great a People ſhould depend upon the underſtanding and affections of ſo few, and that the whole City muſt be without a juſt means to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve themſelves, or to remedy things that are any wayes amiſſe, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the Lord Major and Aldermen will aſſent, And that thoſe whom the People yeerly chooſe, and principally intruſt, ſhould be made uſeleſſe at their pleaſure. And themſelves eſtated with ſuch a power, that no Authority in the City can call them to an account in caſes of miſ-government, is ſo pernitiouſly obſtructive and intolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, as is not to be pleaded, but <hi>to the enſlaving of the People.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Whereas of Right, the People of the City are a free People, and are not to be bound or concluded, but by their own conſents, or by the major part of thoſe they yeerly chooſe to give their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents in common and free Councell, who are Commonners choſen from amongſt themſelves, with reference to their Conſciences, and good affections. In whom the concluding law-making power of the City juſtly is. It being deſtructive and improper that it ſhould
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:113245:14"/>
be eſtated in two diſtinct juriſdictions. And therefore, ſince wee have none to open our griefes unto, but unto you, And that it is thought convenient, that wee ſhould apply our ſelves to this Court in whatſoever we deſire to preſent unto the Parliament.</p>
                        <p>Wee moſt earneſtly intreat you to ſhake off all pretences of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatives, by which (and the like) the Citie and Common-wealth have been moſt groſſely inſlaved, and that you will reduce your ſelves into ſo proper and juſt a method of proceeding, as may ſtand with the condition of a free people, and conduce to the remedying of all grievances, and removall of all our afflictions.</p>
                        <p>Unto which end we humbly propoſe to your grave conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as followeth.</p>
                        <p n="1">I. <hi>That you will be pleaſed to Order a Court of Common Councell once every week to meet without warning upon a certaine day, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe houre, and to publiſh the ſame, that all the Inhabitants of the City may be informed thereof.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="2">II. <hi>That you will alſo publiſh your readineſſe to receive all Informati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Petitions from any of the Inhabitants, there having been many moſt neceſſary and uſefull things ſtiffled for want of incouragement in this kind.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="3">III. <hi>That you will reſolve within your ſelves, to maintaine the Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence and freedome of your Court,</hi> As namely,</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>To take into your Conſiderations, and freely to debate whatſoever the preſent or greater part ſhall thinke meet and neceſſary. To Vote and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude whatſoever to the major part ſhall ſeem good: To continue the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Seſſion or Court, as the preſent occaſions ſhall require, To adjourne to what day and time ſhall by the greater part be thought convenient, over and beſides the ſet weekly</hi> Court, <hi>without which, and the due Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations of all reaſonable Orders, as by your wiſedome ſhall be provided, you will appeare to every juditious underſtanding, but as a meer ſhadow of Power, and no wayes helpfull.</hi> And therefore,</p>
                        <p n="4">IV. <hi>That you will be pleaſed to make a perpetuall ſtanding Order, or Law, that whatſoever Perſon or Perſons ſhall from henceforth by ſecret or open meanes endeauour to deprive the Court of</hi> Common-Councell <hi>of the foreſaid Rights, Freedoms or Priviledges (in the vindicating where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſome members of this Court then Commoners expreſt much zeale a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt that obſtinate Lord Major</hi> Gurney, <hi>and his perverſe Aſſociates)
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:113245:14"/>
ſhall be inſtantly disfranchiſed, and otherwiſe puniſhed, as ſhall ſeem good to the Juſtice of this Court.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Theſe wee moſt earneſtly intreate may be ſpeedily eſtabliſhed, as being the only meanes to incourage your Petitioners, and all other well-affected People, to ſtudy and preſent you with ſuch materialls as may happily tend to give a ſpeedy end to all our miſeries.</p>
                        <closer>And wee ſhall ever pray, &amp;c.</closer>
                        <argument>
                           <p>This Petition was delivered the <hi>15.</hi> of <hi>April, 1645.</hi> to the Common-Councell of <hi>London,</hi> ſitting at <hi>Guild-hall.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </argument>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p n="6">6. Sir <hi>John Lenthall</hi> having acted and done many things of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary prejudice againſt the State, one Captaine <hi>Cob,</hi> a ſea-Captaine, and then Priſoner in the hands of Sir <hi>John Lenthall,</hi> out of duty and affection to the well-fare of the Publique, informed by a Letter the <hi>Speaker</hi> of the Houſe of Commons of it, and ſent his Letter by the hands of one Mrs <hi>Jencts,</hi> who faithfully delivered it to him, and by her importunity to ſome that belonged to the ſaid <hi>Speaker</hi> for an Anſwer to it, the ſaid Captaine <hi>Cob</hi> was brought out of Priſon to the Houſe of Commons door, as he thought to juſtifie the ſaid Letter, who had brought along with him three or foure Witneſſes, to prove all the particulars mentioned<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in the ſaid Letter.</p>
            <p>But the <hi>Speaker,</hi> contrary to his duty, never cauſed him to be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in, but only ſent him out word, that he ſhould goe home againe, and he would ſhortly come over to his brother Sir <hi>Johns</hi> Houſe, and ſpeak with him there, who accordingly did, but would admit none to be preſent to heare what paſſed amongſt them there; yet <hi>Cob,</hi> as ſoone as he came into the Priſon amongſt his fellows, gave unto them a true Relation, upon his Reputation, of what paſſed amongſt them, which as they averre, was to this effect; as ſoon as he came up, ſaith the Speaker, Sir doe you know me, yes ſir, ſaith <hi>Cob,</hi> I know you to be Speaker of the Houſe of Commons, which was the reaſon I writ to you, judging you the fitteſt man to bring to light ſo great a buſineſſe of importance, as I have to make known to you, for the good of the State and Kingdome, then the <hi>Speaker</hi> ſhewed him his
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:113245:15"/>
Letter, and asked him if he would juſtifie it, and he told him, yes, and a great deale more, if he would doe his duty, in making it tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly knowne to the Honourable Houſe of Comm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ns.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Speaker</hi> turning himſelf to his Brother, ſaid, Sir <hi>John,</hi> if this be true, heare is enough to hang you, well Sir, ſaith Sir <hi>John;</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as he chargeth me of letting <hi>Violet</hi> goe twiſe to <hi>Oxford,</hi> during the time that hee and Sir <hi>Baſſell Brooke</hi> were contriving their Plot a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the City; you know I never let him goe but once, and then I had your warrant for it; well, well, ſaid the Speaker, Captaine <hi>Cob,</hi> I ſee you are an honeſt man, and much wronged by your adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, but ſhake hands and be friends with Sir <hi>John,</hi> and I will get you your Liberty, ſo they parted.</p>
            <p>But Captaine <hi>Cob</hi> perceiving the <hi>Speaker</hi> did nothing in it, but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to ſmother it, ſent a true Copy of his Letters, that he had ſent to the Speaker, to Mr. <hi>William Fendry</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> with <hi>Ellen Thomas,</hi> her information about the threeſcore thouſand pounds of Sir <hi>Baſſel Brookes,</hi> that then was in Sir <hi>Johns</hi> hands, which Letter and Information the ſaid <hi>Pendry</hi> communicated to two Knights that are members of the Committee of both Kingdomes, who took no more care then the Speaker to have it brought to light, nor the 60000<abbr>l.</abbr> attached, and now it is upon the ſtage, before the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee of Examination, the Chaireman of which, <hi>Juſtice Whittiker,</hi> with Mr. <hi>Knightly</hi> and Sir <hi>Robert Pye,</hi> who is deſired to remember a Letter that was going to Don <hi>Cottington,</hi> &amp;c. have not dealt fairely in the buſineſſe, as both the Informers, and ſome of the 6. Citizens that were permitted into the Committe, to ſee to the managing of the buſineſſe doe declare.</p>
            <p>And therefore aſſuredly, if ſo foule and hainous a buſineſſe as this is, be ſmothered up againe, I am very confidently perſwaded, ſome one or other will publiſh all the particulars of it (ere long) in print, to the view of all the Commons of <hi>England,</hi> that ſo they may ſee and judge how they are jugled with, by ſome of thoſe they have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed their greateſt truſt in, although Sir <hi>Jo. Lenthall,</hi> and the Spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker have (as it may juſtly be ſuppoſed) ſet Dr. <hi>Baſtwick</hi> at worke to publiſh to the view of the world the innocency of the parties ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed, ſaying in the 8. page of his late book againſt Mr. <hi>Lilburne,</hi> that there is nothing made good againſt them, ſo much as with a ſeeming probabilitie, much leſſe proved, and ſo buſy and earneſt is
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:113245:15"/>
the ſaid <hi>Baſtwick</hi> to defend their rotten Reputations, and their wicked and unjuſt dealings towards the State and Kingdome, that he thinks with his lies and baſe and ſordid language, to ſalve up their credits, and to baffle and juſtle the juſt and honeſt proſecuters out of their juſt wayes and pathes they tread in, to doe the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome faithfull ſervice in bringing treaſon to light.</p>
            <p>Yea, ſo bold and impudent is hee, being back'd by their Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie and Intereſt, that rather then truth ſhall come to light, and their wickedneſſe be diſcovered, he will lay ſuch a blot upon the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi> that will render them ridiculous to all that ſeriouſly read his Book, and conſider that the Parliaments owne Authority hath licenced him to call them Ninneys and Grols.</p>
            <p>For ſaith he in the laſt page of his Book, <hi>For as there is no family, though never ſo honeſt, that hath not a Whore or a Knave of their kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, ſo it is impoſſible in ſuch a great Counſell as the Parliament is, but they ſhould have ſome Ninnyes and Groles, and men that have no more wit, then will reach from their noſe to their mouth:</hi> It were well Dr. <hi>Baſtwick</hi> would doe the Common wealth that ſervice, as to name thoſe men, that ſo ſome men may begge them for fooles, to take up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them ſo high a calling, as to be Law-makers to ſo great and knowing a People, as <hi>England</hi> is, and to have ſo little wit in them.</p>
            <p>Surely this Parliament will be contempteous, not onely to their foes, but alſo to their freinds, and will never ſhake off this blot while they ſit, unleſſe they call him to an account, and make him name whom he meanes, and puniſh that Licencer that durſt be ſo bould, to let ſuch a book be publiſhed <hi>cum privilegio,</hi> to the diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the very Parliament it ſelfe, ſurely Sir <hi>John</hi> and his Brother the Speaker have feed <hi>Baſtwick</hi> well, and are not very ſound, that they put him (their pack-horſe) upon ſuch deſperate courſes to ſalve up their credit, and he hath as little wit or honeſty in him to be ſo earneſt for Sir <hi>John Lenthall</hi> in particular, who is notoriouſly knowne and reputed ſo grand a Knave and Tyrant, by thouſands that know him, as <hi>England</hi> hath not his fellow, being at this preſent Outlawed, and hath ſo continued 3. yeers, and of whom for murder, Cruelty, Bribe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y and Arbitrary Government, and what not, there hath ſo many complaints been made to this preſent Parliament, (though little effect they have taken, by reaſon of the Speakers Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:113245:16"/>
and Intereſt) whoſe common practiſe it is, to walke in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant contempt and violation of the knowne Laws of the Kingdom, and to the making of them null, and of none effect, as much as in him lies, to the ruine and deſtruction of thouſands of the free Deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zons of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For though the Law provide, that if a man in Execution eſcape or walke abroad out of Priſon, the Jaylor is lyable to pay his debt, yet for his own gaine he doth conſtantly doe both, and the undone and wronged Creditor can have no ſatisfaction of him, neither Law nor Juſtice againſt him, by reaſon of the <hi>Speaker</hi> his great fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in the Houſe, ſupporting of him.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>John Lenthal,</hi> beſides his Outlawries, hath dozens of executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons upon him, and yet walkes abroad, and continues keeper of <hi>Kings-Bench</hi> Priſon, and Juſtice of Peace, and as it is reported, is Chairman of a Committee, by means of which, he is inveſted into a Power to cruſh and deſtroy every honeſt man that but opens his mouth to ſpeake of his baſeneſſe and injuſtice, the height of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice and of his Arbitrary and Tyrannicall Government, ſcarcely in <hi>Strafford</hi> to be parralell'd, which is ſo inſupportable to the poor oppreſſed Priſoners in Kings Bench, that they have got a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verbe amongſt them in theſe words;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Lawyers rule Committees, the</hi> Speaker <hi>rules the Lawyers, Sir</hi> John Lenthall <hi>rules the</hi> Speaker; Thomas Dutſon <hi>rules Sir</hi> John Lenthall, <hi>and the Devill rules</hi> Dutſon.</p>
            <p>But for all <hi>Baſtwicks</hi> brags of Sir <hi>John Lenthalls</hi> innocency, if he pleaſe to doe the State ſo much ſervice, as to prevaile with his good friend the <hi>Speaker,</hi> to procure the ſame Court <hi>Marſhall</hi> in <hi>London</hi> that ſate upon the <hi>Hothams,</hi> as ſoon as the Ordinance is paſt, hee ſhall have the names of ſome of reputation in the Kingdome, that will before that Counſell accuſe Sir <hi>John Lenthall</hi> of High Treaſon, and hazard the loſſe of their lives upon the proof of it.</p>
            <p>In the laſt place, the Parliament men ſwear to be at enmitie with indifferencie or newtrallity, which newtrallitie in the <hi>Covenant,</hi> is branded as deteſtable by them, and yet notwithſtanding, divers of them cannot indure them that would have an end of theſe warres ſpeedily; but hate and abhorre all thoſe who with all their might indeavour the end of them: and though ſuch men walke by better principles then taking the <hi>Covenant,</hi> even by Principles ingraven up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:113245:16"/>
their ſoules by God himſelf: yet unleſſe they will take this (im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to be kept) <hi>Covenant,</hi> (the framers and makers of which have runne into wilfull perjury themſelves) they muſt be turned out of Committees and their Regiments disbanded (as in Hartford<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire, &amp;c. and Newters put in their places, that are neither hot nor cold, nor have any other principle whereby to walke, but baſe pecuniary principles and ſelf-Interreſts, and by this meanes the Kingdome is in danger to be utterly deſtroyed, even by ſuch cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous newtrall indifferent Committie-men, and men of excellent publique principles, disfranchiſed, and undenized, contrary to the fundamentall Conſtitutions of the Kingdome, which doe allow none to be ſo dealt with, but only for an act done or committed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the welfare of the Publique.</p>
            <p>And though many conſcientious men have laid out their witts, their time, their paines, their purſes, their blood; yea, and all that in this world is moſt precious to them for the preſervation of the Publique, yet they muſt not ſit in Parliament, though never ſo fit and able, unleſſe they will take this make-bate (perſecuting, ſoul-de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying, <hi>Englands</hi>-dividing, and undoing) <hi>Covenant;</hi> I ſhall there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore deſire all the Commons of <hi>England,</hi> and the Parliament them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, ſeriouſly to read over ſome part of their owne words, in their <hi>Exhortation</hi> to the taking of the <hi>Covenant,</hi> the words thus follow:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And as for thoſe Clergy men who pretend that they (above all others) cannot Covenant to extirpate that Government, becauſe they have (as they ſay) taken a ſolemne Oath to obey the Biſhops,</hi> in licitis &amp; hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtis, <hi>they can tell if they pleaſe, that they that have ſworne obedience to the Laws of the Land, are not thereby prohibited from endeavouring by all lawfull means the abolition of thoſe lawes, when they prove inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient or miſchievous.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And if there ſhould any Oath be found, unto which any Miniſters or others have entered, not warranted by the Laws of God and the Land, in this caſe they muſt teach themſelves and others, that ſuch Oathes call for Repentance, and not obſtinacie in them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O that the Parliament would mind theſe their owne words, and give free leave to ſome of their honeſt fellow Commoners to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate the inconveniency and miſchievouſneſſe of this <hi>Covenant,</hi> and I am confident, it would eaſily and cleerly be made appeare to
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:113245:17"/>
themſelves ſo vild, that they would never inforce it any more, but rather recall it again, <hi>Judg.</hi> 11.30. <hi>Eſt.</hi> 3.10. <hi>Dan.</hi> 3.3. <hi>&amp;c. Mark.</hi> 6.23.</p>
            <p n="12">12. Whether it be not moſt agreeable to Law, Juſtice, equitie and conſcience, and the nature of a Parliament mans place, that during the time of his being a member, hee ſhould lay aſide all places of profit in the Common-wealth, and tend only upon that function, for which he was choſen; or if he be poor, or have loſt his Eſtate, whether he ought not at preſent, to be content with his maſters wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, that is to ſay, with ſo much a day, as the Common-Wealth by the Law of the Land is to pay him for his dayes labour, which is expreſſed in 33. <hi>H.</hi> 8. 11. to be 4<abbr>s.</abbr> 
               <hi>per diem</hi> to every Knight, and to every Citizen and Burgeſſe 2<abbr>s.</abbr> a day, or more, as heretofore hath been accuſtomed, &amp;c. or with ſome reaſonable Competency, being the Commonwealth is grown ſo poor, that it is not able to pay her common Souldiers their 8<abbr>d.</abbr> a day, though they conſtantly adventer their lives to preſerve her, which the Parliament men ſeldome doe, and not to thirſt after great and rich Places, farre leſſe to poſſeſſe or enjoy them.</p>
            <p>Seeing by woefull experience it is found, that the poſſeſſing of them breeds nothing but factions and baſe cowadlineſſe, yea and ſowing up of mens lips, that they dare not ſpeak freely for the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, nor diſpleaſe ſuch and ſuch a faction, for feare of being Voted, and thruſt out of their unfit to be enjoyed Offices, the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth hath juſt cauſe to fear they wil ſet up an intereſt of their owne, deſtructive to that common Intereſt and Freedome, whereof the pooreſt free man in <hi>England</hi> ought to be poſſeſſor, and ſo make this preſent Parliament an everlaſting Parliement, and the Warre a never ending Warre, ſeeing it tends ſo much to the inriching of Parliament men and their Officers, who have already wiſely, as they thinke, fenced themſelves with an Ordinance made the 26. of <hi>June,</hi> 1645. That they ſhall not be called to account for their Maſters the Common-wealths money, nor Plate that once commeth into their fingers.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>But would you have thoſe Parliament men, that had their Places before the Parliament ſate, turned out of theirs?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yes, I would have Sir <hi>Henry Mildmer,</hi> Sir <hi>Henry Vane</hi> the young<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, Soliciter <hi>Saint-John,</hi> Mr. <hi>Holland, &amp;c.</hi> turned out of their Places at preſent, though I conceive it juſt they ſhould be ſecured of the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:113245:17"/>
injoyment of them againe ſo ſoon as the Parliament is ended, for their preſent injoying thereof, ſowes but up their lippes, and makes them they dare neither ſpeake nor doe that they ſhould, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out them is hoped they would (and for avoiding the jealouſie of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiallity) I thinke there is as much Juſtice, to turne them out during the Parliaments continuing, as to turne out Mr. <hi>Greene,</hi> Sir <hi>Robert Harlow,</hi> Sir <hi>Walter Earle,</hi> Mr. <hi>Reynolds,</hi> the <hi>Speaker,</hi> Mr. <hi>Prideaux, &amp;c.</hi> and all the Chancery Judges, for to me it is one of the moſt unjuſt things in the world, that the Law-makers ſhould be the Law executors, ſeeing by that meanes, if they doe never ſo much injuſtice and oppreſſion, a man may ſpend both long time, and all he hath beſides, before ever he can get any Juſtice againſt them, yea, and it may be, hazard the loſſe of his life too.</p>
            <p>And therefore it were a great deal better for the Common-wealth, that all the executors of the Law ſhould be ſuch perſons as doe not in the leaſt belong to the Parliament, that ſo they may not be able to make any fictions to ſave their Lives and Eſtates, when they doe injuſtice: and I am confident, there is never an honeſt-hearted Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament man that meanes well to the Common-Wealth, but he will upon the debating of this needfull point, be of my minde, though it be never ſo contrary to his owne particular Intereſt and profit.</p>
            <p>But you will ſay, This will fetch that gallant man <hi>Cromwell</hi> from the Army, which will be a mighty loſſe to the Kingdome, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he is ſo able and active a Souldier, and ſo extraordinarily belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of the Officers and Souldiers in the Army, yea, and ſuch a ſtay to that unparralleld Generall, Sir <hi>THOMAS FAIRE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FAX.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer, it is very true, that the Kingdome will have a mighty loſſe of him indeed, if he ſhould be taken out of the Army, and be made unſerviceable to them any where elſe; but if he come into the Houſe of Commons (that proper ſeat whereunto hee was choſen,) and doe them ten times more ſervice there, then he doth, or can doe in the Army, what loſſe hath the Common-Wealth then? Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſeriouſly the grand ſervice he did the laſt Winter, when hee was in the Houſe, and ſee whether any action that ever he did in his life can be parralleld to it, and I beleeve it will be found good to have him at home: for he is ſound at the heart, and not rotten cored,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:113245:18"/>
hates particular and ſelfe-Intereſts, and dares freely ſpeake his minde.</p>
            <p>Therefore home with him, as well as the reſt of Parliament-men, according to their owne Ordinance, and let him perfect what he began, and either lay <hi>Mancheſter</hi> flat upon his back, or himſelf, for the beſt ſervice can be done the Kingdome, is to pull out home-bred Traytors, and to helpe to keep and preſerve the <hi>Great Counſell</hi> aright: for if there be Twenty Armies abroad, and your Counſells be not abſolutely ſafe, ſound, and Unanimous at home, you are not ſafe, but ſtill in danger; beſides, I have heard it reported, that hee was about a deſigne of getting a Committee ſet apart, and an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der made and publiſhed to the whole Kingdome, that if any man were unjuſtly oppreſſed by any Member of Parliament, Committe-man, or any other Officers or Miniſters, let him bring his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint, and hee ſhall have a juſt and a faire hearing, and Juſtice done not in words, but in actions upon the Tranſgreſſour.</p>
            <p>O for ſelfe-denying <hi>Cromwell</hi> home againe, to ſet this on foot, which would be a ſalve for all our ſores, and would gaine the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament more ground in one moneth, then their forcing the <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant</hi> will doe in a hundred; And if you will ſeriouſly meditate upon theſe things, you will finde there was a hidden myſtery in ſending him from the Parliament, when he had impeached <hi>Mancheſter,</hi> the freſh pricking of which veine againe, would cauſe good blood to grow in the body of our Common-wealth; and beſides <hi>Cromwell</hi> may reaſonable well be ſpared now from the Army, ſeeing there are ſo many gallant, brave, and true-hearted <hi>Engliſhmen</hi> there beſides himſelf, who are well knowne for their Honeſty, Parts, Valour and Souldiery to the Noble Generall: and beſides, <hi>Cromwell,</hi> if he were at the Houſe, might (if it were thought fit) now and then viſite the Army, to ſolder them together, if there ſhould be any disjoynted, (as I hope there will not) in which Art hee hath good skill, and unfainedly hates all factious pertaking, and baſe ſelfe-gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <p>Againe, Whether is it not agreeable to Law, Juſtice, Equity and Conſcience, ſeeing that by the 4. of <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. 14. that there ſhould be a Parliament once every yeere, and more often, if need require, and in the 36. of <hi>E.</hi> 3. 10. it is inacted, That for maintenance of the Laws, and the redreſſe of divers miſchiefs and grievances, which dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:113245:18"/>
happen, a Parliament ſhall be holden every yeere, as at another time was ordained by a Statute, that ſeeing this preſent Parliament, (by reaſon of the extraordinary neceſſities of the Kingdom) have ſate foure yeeres, and many of the members betray'd their truſt, and thoſe that remaine, ingroſſe Law-making, and alſo Law-executing into their own hands contrary both to reaſon, and to the true in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent and meaning of the Law, which ſaith, <hi>delayes in judgement in other Courts ſhall be redreſſed in Parliament, as alſo falſe judgements and difficult Caſes that ſhall happen, ſhall be there decided:</hi> Read the 14. <hi>E.</hi> 3. 5.</p>
            <p>By which manifeſt abuſing, negligent and not true uſing the Lawes, oppreſſions, miſchiefes and grievances are no leſſe (if not far more) increaſed, then they were before the Parliament began; and many times by the powerfull Intereſt of a Faction in the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to ſave ſome one, two or three of their Members, undeſerving credits; they ſo violate the known, unrepealed, and declared law of the land, yea and their owne Votes, Ordinances, Declarations, and Proteſtations, as if they had never made them; I ſay, all theſe things conſidered, ought not the Free-men of <hi>England,</hi> who have labour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in theſe deſtroying times, both to preſerve the Parliament, and their owne native Freedoms and Birth-rights, not only to chuſe new Members, where they are wanting once every yeere, but alſo to renue and inquire once a yeere, after the behaviour and carriage of thoſe they have choſen.</p>
            <p>And if they finde that ſince they came into the Houſe, they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver made any motions for the publick good, nor ſo much as for theirs that ſent them, but doe ſit like ſo many <hi>Ninneys</hi> and <hi>Groles,</hi> that have no more wit in them, then will reach from their noſes to their mouthes, as Doctour <hi>Baſtwick</hi> ſaies, or have any way been unfaithfull and unſerviceable to the publique, or groundedly ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected ſo to be, that then thoſe that chuſe and ſent them, may have liberty to chuſe more faithfull, able and better men in their places, for ſtanding water will ſpeedily corrupt, if it have not freſh running ſprings to feed it, though it were never ſo pure at the firſt.</p>
            <p>Therefore I earneſtly deſire all true-hearted: Free-men of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> to have a care in their preſent new choices, and ſeriouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, that Gallant man, Major <hi>George Withers</hi> advice to them in his late Book, eſpecially his 20. page, who there ſaith, <hi>Some men
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:113245:19"/>
give their voices to their freinds, ſome to their Landlords, ſome to the richeſt (and hee forſooth muſt needs be the wiſeſt) mens merits are meaſured by the aker, weighed by the pound, ſo let a Beaſt be Lord of beaſts, and poſſeſſe many acres of durt, hee ſhall be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred to be a Parliament-man, in admiration of his wealth, and not wit: although (as</hi> Varro <hi>ſaith of a ſwine) he hath no more ſoule then will ſerve in ſtead of ſalt to keep his body from putrifying.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But who thinkes upon the poor wiſe man, who as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>ſaved the City?</hi> who thinks of the juſt man, whoſe integrity keeps Gods bleſſing amongſt us, and us together amongſt our ſelves? No not one; who wonders then to ſee a crooked repreſentation of a crooked Commonwealth it is no true glaſſe that ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ts not a ſhadow as crooked and deformed as the ſubſtance: but above all others, have care of chuſing Lawyers, as the ſame Author in his late Poems called <hi>Vox Pacifica,</hi> page 183. ſaith of them; for if the Common-wealth had Peace with their profeſſed enemies; yet they will rein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe.</p>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>—Your Quarrells, elſe, aſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>one as you agree:</l>
                  <l>By their formalities, and flow proceeding,</l>
                  <l>Your remedy f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r injuries is made</l>
                  <l>A miſchief, the diſeaſe oft times exceeding;</l>
                  <l>And if ſome eye unto them be not had,</l>
                  <l>So many places in your Parliament,</l>
                  <l>They will ſupply, and fill ſo many Chaires</l>
                  <l>In your Committees; that, much detriment</l>
                  <l>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto the Subject; and ſome cloſe impaires</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Of <hi>Publique Freedomes</hi> (e're you be aware)</l>
                  <l>Which ſlip upon you, if you have not care.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>So ſtrong a party they have alwayes had,</l>
                  <l>That your <hi>great-Charter,</hi> which doth interdict</l>
                  <l>Delay of Juſtice, was in that point made</l>
                  <l>(Ere ſince the <hi>Grant</hi>) a Law without effect.</l>
                  <l>But when their Courts, and practiſes have reach'd</l>
                  <l>Oppreſſions height; they, as the Clergie were;</l>
                  <l>Shall downe into another Orb be fetch'd,</l>
                  <l>And taught to keep a conſtant motion there:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="35" facs="tcp:113245:19"/>This worke, upon ſome Court hath been begun,</l>
                  <l>Another time, it ſhall be fully done.</l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <p>And as the worthy Authour of that late ſheet of paper, called <hi>Some Advertiſements, for the new Election of Burgeſſes for the Houſe of Commons,</hi> ſaith in his 6. page.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Take heed how you fill up Elections with theſe kind of men</hi> (meaning Lawyers) <hi>the Recorder of every Borough will of courſe looke to be cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen; as being the mouth of his Corporation: but it is a Cuſtome not fit for the neceſſitie of theſe times, our affaires require rather</hi> Stateſ-men <hi>then Lawyers;</hi> my Reaſons againſt ſuch Elections follow:</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>The Knowledge of the Common Law, doth no way conduce to the making of a States-man: it is a confined and topicall kind of Learning, Calculated only for the Meridian of</hi> Weſtminſter-Hall; <hi>and reacheth no further then</hi> Dover. <hi>Tranſplant a Common Lawyer to</hi> Calice, <hi>and his head is no more uſefull there, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n a Sun-dyals in a grave: who ever heard of the Polyticks written in Law-French?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>If the making and penning of good Lawes were the worke of theſe times (as they are not) it were not wiſedome to chuſe Mercinary Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers to make Lawes: becauſe they are the firſt men to invent ſubtilties to evade them, and make them uſeleſſe; and will pen them obſcurely on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to procure themſelves work in the interpretation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Lawyers, being a bold and talketive kinde of men; will intrude themſelves into the Chaires of all Committees, where (being accuſtomed to take fees) they will under-hand protect delinquents, and their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed Eſtates with tricks and devices.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>The Reformation of Courts of Juſtice, is a worke of abſolute neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, without which (though the ſword of the Lord returneth again into its ſcabbard, ſo that you have no warre yet) you ſhall have no Peace: but if you have many Lawyers, they will never ſuffer any effectuall Law to paſſe for this purpoſe: Becauſe they yet move by the corruption and delayes of the Law, then by the Law it ſelf:</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>It is neceſſary to make a Law for limitation of exorbetant fees, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tortion, and prevarication (or colluſion) amongſt Lawyers, as it is uſed in other Countries.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>It is neceſſary to limit the certaine number of practiſers in each Court, that they ſwarme not (like Locuſts) over the land, devouring and impoveriſhing it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:113245:20"/>Theſe bleſſings you will never attaine unto, unleſſe God give you the wiſedom to avoide ſuch <hi>Elections:</hi> lay to your hearts ſinne as well as the ſhame and ſmart, of oppreſſions and tranſgreſſions of lawyers, and you will finde that the cries of the oppreſſed have been a principall motive to draw downe Gods vengeance upon this mournfull Land.</p>
            <p>Was ever ſo deſperate a wound given to the Lawes, Liberties and properties, as the predetermined judgement of Ship-mony. Who gave that blow? Judges. What were they? Theeves <hi>cum privilegio Rege majeſtatis,</hi> who bought Juſtice by whole-ſale, and ſold it by Retaile? Who aſſiſted them? Lawyers; who undertaking to pleade for their Clyants againſt it, (pretending one thing, and doing ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing) for the moſt part: and betrayed the Cauſe, all to get fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour and preferrment; and yet ſuch proceedings<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> were both againſt the Judges, and the <hi>Coronation Oath;</hi> upon an extrajuditiall opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on colluſively given: (for ſaith the Record) <hi>Sacramentum Domini Regis erga populum ſuum habent ad cuſtodiendum:</hi> But our Judges, (though more wicked) have the happineſſe to live in a more wicked age, and out-live their crimes, paying onely a ſmall part by way of fine: and enjoying there to their ſtollen treaſures: and after they had made Peace as devouring as warre, and the Law as cruell as the Sword; who's that is not a better Chriſtian then theſe Brothers of the <hi>Coyfe,</hi> brothers in evill: will not cry out with <hi>Epicures,</hi> that God takes no more care what men doe on this earthly balke, then man doth what <hi>Ants</hi> doe on an <hi>Em<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t-hill;</hi> when <hi>Verres:</hi> (being <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſull</hi> of <hi>Cicily,</hi>) had pilled that <hi>Province,</hi> and (other <hi>Pro-Conſulls,</hi> and <hi>Pro-Praetors</hi> were puni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hed for leſſer Extortions) he laughing at their fooliſh moderation, vaunted to his Brother <hi>Ty<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>kedes:</hi> that he had got enough to buy the freindſhip of the <hi>Senate,</hi> and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation, of a rich and Honourable man: So our Judges enjoy their crimes, and the prize and reward of them: Nay, they grow fatt and proſper upon the anger of God and man, whileſt this Land groanes under the ſad weight of the <hi>Sword, Peſtilence,</hi> and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, the effects of their inju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tice: but through whoſe favour is it they have not expiated their Crimes with their blood: and waſhed away the Guilt of the Land<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but the <hi>Lawyers?</hi> who wiſely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider it may be their own Caſe another day.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:113245:20"/>I have ſhewed you how unſafe it is to truſt Mercinary-men with making or keeping of your Lawes; I will epitomize what I have ſaid in <hi>Pleniea's</hi> words <hi>(in Panegyr. ad Trajanum,)</hi> Heretofore we were laden with our Crimes, now we are oppreſſed with our Lawes: and it is to be feared, leaſt the Common-wealth (though founded by the Lawes) be confounded by the Lawes (or rather by the Lawyers.)</p>
            <p>Likewiſe to this purpoſe read what the Authour (reputed to be a member of the Aſſembly, as well as he that writes the <hi>Brotherly and friendly Cenſure of Mr.</hi> Prinnes 4. <hi>late Queries:</hi>) in his Antidote againſt the ſame 4. dangerous Queries, <hi>pag.</hi> 3. ſaith, That if the thing be granted, that he diſputes, for Judges will be taught, <hi>That they judge not for man, but for the Lord, who is with them in judgement,</hi> peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple will grow more peaceable and free from continuall contentions: Lawyers ſhall not get the wealth of the Land into their hands by <hi>fiſhing in troubled waters:</hi> incouraging men in unlawfull and quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relous ſuites, pleading wicked Cauſes for large Fees, prolonging ſuites; and making men ſpend in long ſuite unto twiſe the value of their juſt Right, and debt for which they ſue, and by taking treeble fees, and keeping them, though they faile their Clyant, and have beene imployed at other <hi>Barres,</hi> when his Cauſe was to be pleaded.</p>
            <p>Godlineſſe and <hi>true Religion</hi> being increaſed by faithfull Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and godly Diſcipline, in the hearts of men, will make the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth free from the neceſſity of many <hi>Lawyers,</hi> which the learned Philoſopher held to be a Plague in a State and Kingdome: and therefore it is no marvell that the corrupt ones of that Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, are deadly enemies to the Maintenance, Honour, and other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragements of the true Miniſtery of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alſo:</hi> Read what that honeſt Author (and true principl'd Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealths man:) of the little booke intituled, <hi>A Helpe to the Right underſtanding of Mr.</hi> Wil. Prynne, ſaith of Lawyers; and lay all the aforecited Authors together, and you will eaſily finde, they make it evidently appeare, that there is as little uſe of Lawyers to be in the Houſe of Commons, as there is of a Plague or Peſtil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nce, or of the Biſhops and Popiſh Lords in the Honourable Houſe of Peeres; their Intereſt being both as Delatory, and as deſtructive to the true Peace, Proſperity and well-fare of the Common-wealth of diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:113245:21"/>
               <hi>England:</hi> for the procuring of which, as principall helpes and meanes under the powerfull and wiſe diſpoſing Providence of the Lord <hi>JEHOVAH,</hi> who in his owne due time, (as <hi>Mordecai</hi> ſaid to <hi>Eſther, Eſt.</hi> 4.14. and <hi>Iſa.</hi> 63.3. <hi>when all means faileth, is alone able with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out and beyond all meanes, to bring Salvation by his owne out-ſtretched Arme,</hi> Yet let not us be idle or ſecure, but obſerve and indeavour theſe inſuing means for our part.</p>
            <p n="1">I. <hi>By Petitioning, and by all other lawfull wayes and addreſſes, ſtrive to procure from the Parliament, and all other juſt Authority, that they (according to their duty, Oath, and Profeſſion; yea, and our truſt repoſed in them) will Adminiſter J<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>STICE impartially, (according to that loud and earneſt deſire of diſtreſſed and Impriſoned Lieutenant Colonell LILB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RNE, in that late</hi> Letter, <hi>(which frequently is called his,) and according to thoſe ſad and lamenting Expreſſions in that juſt complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Epiſtle (of an</hi> Utter Barreſter <hi>to his ſpeciall freind,) called</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands Miſery and Remedy,) <hi>and that without turning either to the right hand, or to the left, or knowing of any Relation either to Father, Mother, Siſter, Brother, Kinſman or other; or without regarding of any Faction, either Popiſh, Epiſcopall, Presbyterian, Independant, Separate or Anabaptiſt, but Cordially to doe every one Juſtice, becauſe it is juſt: and ſeverely to puniſh all perverters of Juſtice, whoſoever they be: one Moneths doing of which, would procure the Parliament more Cordiall freinds then the fighting of all their Armies, or the forcing of all their Covenants, or the Preſſing of all their Souldiers, or perſecuting all their Sectaries will doe in ten moneths ſpace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">II. <hi>To endeavour to ſet the City of</hi> London <hi>right in the enjoyment of her Priviledges: (being the Metropolis of</hi> England, <hi>that ſhee may indeed be a true Preſident to all the Cities and Corporations in the Kingdome, and a ballance to all the Tyrants, or Arbytrary-principl'd men in the ſame:) the means to ſet her right, is firſt, for the Commons to get a Copy of their Charters, and tranſlate them into Engliſh, and print, them, that ſo every free-man may ſee and know his own rights, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour the more earneſtly the exemplary puniſhment of the infringers and incroachers thereupon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">III. <hi>To riſe as one man under faithfull, honeſt, experienced, conſtant, well-affected Commanders, ſuch as thoſe that riſe, ſhall chuſe to adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture their lives with; and beleager all the Kings Garriſons before the ſtorme grow ſo great in the North, that no man dare travell under paine
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:113245:21"/>
of his life, according thoſe honeſt and good Directions lately printed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which are intituled,</hi> Englands Cordiall Phyſick.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. <hi>To call to a juſt and ſtrict account all Fingerers, and Receivers of money, whatſoever, even Parliament men as well as others; for they are all but the Common-wealths ſervants) and ſeverely (according to the greateſt pennalty of any declared and unrepealed Law) to puniſh all thoſe that have any wayes cheated and cozened the Common-wealth, and unjuſtly made themſelves rich by her treaſure now in the time of their great richer, and her extreame poverty; and for future time, to make a Law to puniſh with death all ſuch groſſe tranſgreſſors, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve to have their skinnes flead off, and ſtopt full of ſtraw, and hung up publikely in the places where they ſo unjuſtly executed their undeſerved Offices, and deceived their owne Nation to inrich themſelves, to the ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifying of all ſuch as ſhall ſucceed them in their places, from the acting of ſuch unchriſtian<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yea, and worſe then Heathen-like Roaguery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For I am confident, that the portion of all ſuch covetous State-robbers, Nationall Fellons, mighty thieves, and ſecret Traytors will be ſuch as are deſcribed (or painted lively in their colours) throughout the Twentieth Chapter o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Job,</hi> from the fourth Verſe, which I expreſſe here at large, and more Scriptures after them, for the uſe of thoſe that have no <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bles,</hi> to read (they are become ſo dear, and Monopolized like other things, as ſhall yet hereafter ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare,) the words a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e theſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Knoweſt not thus this of old, ſince man was placed upon the earth, that the triumphing of the wicked is ſhort, and the joy of the hypocrite but for a moment. Though his Exce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lency mount up to the heavens, and his head reach unto the Clouds, yet he ſhall periſh for ever, like his owne dung: they which have ſeen him, ſhall ſay, Where is hee?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>He ſhall flie away as a dreame, and ſhall not be found, yea, he ſhalbe chaſed away as a Viſion of the night, the eye alſo which ſaw him, ſhall ſee him no more, neither ſhall his Place any more behold him. His Children ſhall ſeek to pleaſe the Poore, and his hands ſhall reſtore their goods: His bones are full of the f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rme of his youth, which ſhall lie downe with him in the duſt. Though wickedneſſe be ſweet in his mouth, though hee hide it under his tongue: though he ſpare it, and forſake it not, but keep it ſtill within his mouth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Yet his meat in his bowels is turned, it is the gall of aſpes within him: He hath ſwallowed down riches, and hee ſhall vomite them up againe,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:113245:22"/>
God ſhall caſt them out of his belly: He ſhall ſuck the poyſon of Aſpes, the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ipers tongue ſhall ſlay him: He ſhall not ſee the Rivers, the ſhods, the brookes of honey and butter; That which he laboured for, hee ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore, and ſhall not ſwallow it downe; according to his ſubſtance ſhall the reſtitution be, and he ſhall not rejoyce therein.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Becauſe he hath oppreſſed, and hath forſaken the poor, becauſe he hath violently taken away an houſe which he builded not: ſurely hee ſhall not finde quietneſſe in his belly, hee ſhall not ſave of that which hee deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>There ſhall none of his meat be left, he ſhall be in ſtraites; every hand of the wicked ſhall come upon him: When he is about to fill his belly, God ſhall caſt the fury of his wrath upon him, and ſhall raine it upon him, while he is eating.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>He ſhall flie from the iron weapon, and the bow of ſteel ſhall ſtrike him through: it is drawne, and commeth of the body: yea, the gliſtering ſword commeth out of his gall; terrours are upon him: all darkneſſe ſhall be hid in his ſecret places; a fire not blowne ſhall conſume him: it ſhall goe ill with him that is left in his Tabernable. The heaven ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veale his iniquity; and the earth ſhall riſe up againſt him: the increaſe of his Houſe ſhall depart, and his goods ſhall flow away in the day of his wrath: This is the portion of a wicked man from God, and the heritage appointed unto him by God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Cnſider and apply theſe Judgements to your ſelves yee wicked <hi>Lawyers,</hi> (if you apprehend your ſelves to be guilty of the blood, and of grinding the faces of the poor, by your profeſſions, and eſpecially you grand <hi>Lawyers,</hi> (who are out of your element) in the Houſe of Commons, by your practiſes.)</p>
            <p>And as the Pſalmiſt ſaith well of wicked men, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.5. <hi>&amp;c. They are not in trouble as other men, neither are they plagued like other men: their eyes ſtand out with fatnes, they have more then their heart can wiſh, they are corrupt and ſpeak wickedly concerning oppreſſion, they ſpeake fooliſhly, they ſet their mouth againſt the heavens, and their tongue walketh through the earth; therefore the people returne hither, and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of a full cup are wrung out to them. And they ſay, bow doth God know? and is there knowledge in the Moſt High: Behold theſe are the ungodly, who proſper in the world, they increaſe in riches.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But in the 18. verſe it is ſaid; <hi>Surely thou (O Lord) didſt ſet them in ſlippery places, thou caſteſt them down into deſtruction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:113245:22"/>And in the 49. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> hee ſaith, <hi>Bee not thou afraid, when one is made rich, when the glory of his houſe is increaſed, for when hee dieth, hee ſhall carry nothing away, his glory ſhall deſcend after him, &amp;c. And in the</hi> 50. <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 16, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But unto the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, God ſaith, <hi>What haſt thou to doe with my ſtatutes, or that thou ſhouldeſt take my Covenant in thy mouth: ſeeing thou hateſt inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and caſteſt my words behind thee. When thou ſaweſt a thief, then then conſentedſt with him, and haſt been partaker with Adulterers. Thou giveſt thy mouth to evill, and thy tongue frameth deceit. Thou ſitteſt and ſpeakeſt againſt thy brother, thou ſlandereſt thine owne mothers ſonne. Theſe things haſt thou done, and I have kept ſilence: thou thoughteſt that I was altogether ſuch a one as thy ſelf; but I will reprove thee, and ſet them in Order before thine eyes. Now conſider this, yee that forget GOD, leſt I teare you in pieces, and there be none to deliver. Whoſo offereth praiſe, glorifieth me, and to him that ordereth his converſation aright, will I ſhew the ſalvation of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But as the Prophet</hi> Jeremiah <hi>ſaith,</hi> chap. 23. &amp;c. <hi>But this people hath a revolting and rebellious heart; they are revolted and gone: neither ſay they in their heart, let us now feare the Lord, our GOD, that giveth rain, both the former and the latter in his ſeaſon, hee reſerveth unto us the very appointed weeks of the harveſt: your iniquities hath turned away theſe things, and your ſinnes have withdrawen good things from you. For a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong my people are found wicked men; they lay wait, as hee that layeth ſnares, they ſet a trap to catch men. As a cage is full of birds, ſo are their houſes full of deceit, therefore they are became great, and waxed rich. They are grown fat, they ſhine, yea, they overpaſſe the deeds of the wickod, they judge not the cauſe, the cauſe of the fatherleſſe; yet they proſper, and the right of the needy doe they not judge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Shall I not viſite for theſe things, ſaith the Lord, ſhall not my ſoul be revenged on ſuch a Nation as this? A wonderfull and horrible thing is committed in the Land, the Prophets Propheſie, falſly, and the Prieſts heare rule by that means, and my people love to have it ſo, and what will yee doe in the end thereof?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to returne to our former matter, eſpecially the grievances of the Nation; (through the miſtake of the Printer, in omitting of ſome Manuſcripts) and the abſence of the Author, when the Monopolies in the former part of this Book were expreſſed; as chiefly that ſoul-ſtarving, or murthering Monopoly, in hindering the free paſſage of
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:113245:23"/>
the Goſpel, by extorting the prices of Bibles, which the falſe ſelf-loving Stationers, as deadly enemies to all goodneſſe, have been en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprizing a long time to obtaine, and againſt all common freedom, to engroſſe into their owne hands the ſole and only ſelling of them, by which meanes, they intend to ſell at what rates ſoever they pleaſe, though already they ſell at double the rate that honeſt wel-affected Common-wealths men may print and ſell them, and alſo be conſcionable gainers by them:</p>
            <p>So of all Monopolies or Patents, next the monopolizing of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groſſing the Preaching of Gods Word into the Tything and gripe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing clawes of the Clergy; this is the moſt wicked and intollerable, becauſe it deprives many, both poore ſervants, and others of meane condition to buy any Bibles at all, by reaſon of the extraordinary dearth or dearneſſe of them, that thereby they might be inſtructed in the way to heaven and happineſſe; and taught their duty alſo to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards their Maſters, and the Magiſtrates; whereby it is evident, that thoſe Stationers, thus enterprising, are ſelf-ſeekers, and as great ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to the Common-wealth, as they are to all goodneſſe.</p>
            <p>And beſides, they employ the Biſhops old Theeves and Roagues about their robbing affaires, as <hi>Hunſcott</hi> their Beadle for one, and a tall pale-faced fellow for another, who lately with their baſe crue of robbing Partners, under pretence of Parliamentary Authority, to ſearch for dangerous Bookes, have robbed divers honeſt mens hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in <hi>London,</hi> who have been the Parliaments beſt freinds and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, and particularly, Lievtenant Colonell <hi>Lilburnes</hi> houſe, who being Priſoner in New-gate, and his wife with him, and the great with Childe, &amp; neer her time, thoſe robbers took advantage of their abſence.</p>
            <p>And none being in the Houſe, but an old Gentle-woman at that time, whom they much frighted; as they did a young Gentle-woman in another place, to the great danger of her life (inſomuch that ſhe cryeth out in her extreame-Fever, <hi>Hunſcott, Hunſcott,</hi>) they ranne up into the Chambers, &amp; ſtole out of his wives Drawers, divers pieces of her Child-bed linnen<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ſuch other things as they plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and refuſed to ſhew the Old-woman what they had ſtollen, though ſhee earneſtly intreated them.</p>
            <p>And in other the Parliaments freinds houſes, under the colour of Parliamentary Authority, they at leaſt doe rob all choice old books,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:113245:23"/>
as well as new, upon all occaſions of ſuch grievous oppreſſions, and unexpected perſecutions.</p>
            <p>And not only hath this baſe fellow <hi>Hunſcott</hi> this ſo needfull and profitable Office of Robbing, but it is reported, that hee hath alſo another as needfull and profitable, for he gathereth the Exciſe for Cattell, and Hats, &amp;c. which with the former, is eſteemed to be worth 500<abbr>l.</abbr> 
               <hi>per annum</hi> to him.</p>
            <p>Oh! what a cleer demonſtration of future and intended ſlavery may be well and cleerly perceived by any (who have but halfe an eye) to begin againe among us (though after more hidden and obſcured wayes then formerly) when ſuch ſturdy Roagues, bold Robbers, ſhameleſſe covetous, and impudent Tyrants as this, or his fellows, are authorized and ſent from high Judicatories, upon ſuch ungodly &amp; barbarous deſignes, &amp; inhumane enterprizes, &amp; yet found good enough alſo to be imployed in the great Affaires of the Kingdom!</p>
            <p>Is there never a conſcientious nor honeſt man left unkilled, exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led or impriſoned, that hath the feare of God, &amp; done good &amp; faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſervice to the State, there would be ſome colour of excuſe, that ſuch abjects and off-ſcourings of mankind ſhould be accepted, and well-deſerving worthy men quite rejected? Well, theſe are brave times for the wicked, who are advanced by the ruine of the godly, the allowed thiefe permitted to rob and deſtroy the honeſt man, the rich to rob, plunder and ſequeſtrate the poore, untill they can get no more, but when they have gotten all, and done with all what they pleaſe, it reſts only that the poore alſo, in their turne, render them the like meaſure, and finde out their Riches for the States ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, which all this heavy time they have ſaved, whiles poore mens eſtates have been exceedingly deſtroyed.</p>
            <p>But as the Water-men at <hi>Queen-hive</hi> doe uſually cry, <hi>Weſtward hough, hough,</hi> ſo according to the preſent current of the times, moſt honeſt men have more then cauſe to cry in the Water-mens lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, <hi>Aegypt hough, hough, the houſe of Bondage, ſlavery, oppreſſion, taxation, heavy and cruell, heavy and cruell, wee can no longer beare it, we can no longer beare it, wee can no longer beare it; wee are as much pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked &amp; forced to caſt off all our yoakes and croſſes from our ſhoulders (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept only that of Perſecution) as ever any people or Nations, though no People or Nation under heaven have been more free, beneficiall and help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to thoſe whom wee intruſted to help and deliver as from Oppreſſion,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:113245:24"/>
which ſaith the</hi> Wiſe-man, <hi>is enough to make wiſe-men mad.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>According to the Parliaments Declaration, in their own words, expreſſed on the ſecond page of this book, is it not juſtly ſaid, that in the Generall of an Army ſhould turn the mouthes of his Cannons againſt his owne Souldiers, would not that his attempt contrary to the nature of his truſt and place committed unto him, <hi>ipſo facto,</hi> eſtate the Army in a right of diſobedience, (even by ſtanding on their own defence, as the Parliament themſelves doe (and we alſo in helping them, or elſe where had they been, againſt the fury of the King, which <hi>Salomon</hi> calleth, <hi>like the roaring of a Lion;</hi> except wee thinke that obedience binds men to cut their owne throates, or at leaſt their companions, ſo (as they truly teach us) it is the equitie, and not the Letter of the Law, unto which wee muſt have recourſe in our greateſt neceſſity, as the Parliament themſelves were forced to doe, and ſtill doth in this their owne extremity.</p>
            <p>But ſome will ſay, that our bondage is not yet ſo bad as that of <hi>Aegypt</hi> was, for all the Jewes were in great bondage under the <hi>Egyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> and yet many of ours are exempted: unto that I yeeld, and doe confeſſe, that few of our great and mighty men doe either work the clay, or make the bricks; but they lay either all, or moſt part of the burthen on the poor by heavy labour, and ſweat of their browes in the heat of the day, not only in working the clay, and making of the bricks, but if they doe complaine to <hi>Higher Powers,</hi> upon their cruell and Tyrannous <hi>Task-maſters,</hi> they are ſo farre from getting any kind of Juſtice, that becauſe they moaned and complained, and groaned under ſuch heavy and grievous burdens, that they were not able any longer to beare or indure, they are further ordained (even for their complaining) to gather ſtubble too, becauſe they are ſo idle.</p>
            <p>Innumerable inſtances there are throughout theſe three mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and bleeding Kingdomes, to prove all theſe buſineſſes, but I will onely chuſe a Citie inſtance, and let every man who is in his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion after that manner grieved and wronged, turne the ſimile home to himſelf, according to his ſmart; Though the poore Hat-makers, who earne their living with heavy and, hot labours, both early and late, doe pay Exciſe both for all the materialls, and fire which they uſe, for the bread they eate, for the liquor they drinke, and clothes they weare, yet when they have made their Hatts, and
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:113245:24"/>
done all they can with great trouble and toyle, day and night, they are forced to pay Exciſe over againe out of their very labour, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding it was both ſo deare and heavy in buying all the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaries before.</p>
            <p>O cruell, pitifull, lamentable and intollerable Bondage, no long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to be indured, ſuffered, nor undergone, the burdens being far hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vier then the poore labourers can beare! and yet the <hi>Spirituall Taſk-maſters</hi> doe gape, and roar like Lions for their prey of Tythes, alſo over, above, and beſides all, without any kinde of pitie, compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion or commiſeration, in theſe grievous daies of affliction.</p>
            <p>When this Kingdom was in any way or poſſibility of ſubſiſtance, the auntient cuſtome was, that Taxations ſhould be raiſed by way of Subſidie, which is the moſt juſt, equitable, and reaſonable way of all, for it ſets every tub on its owne bottome, it layes the burthen upon the ſtrong ſhoulders of the rich, who onely are able to beare it, but ſpareth and freeth the weake ſhoulders of the poore, becauſe they are ſcarcely able to ſubſiſt, pay rent, and maintain their fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies.</p>
            <p>But our new invented pay, layes the burden heavily upon the poore, and men of middle quality or condition, without all diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ſcarcely maketh the rich touch it with one of their fingers: yea, many of them are more and more advanced in their proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous eſtate, through the great ruines, diſtractions, and miſeries of the Kingdome, by their great ſalleries they have for executing their places, as 500<abbr>l.</abbr> 1000<abbr>l.</abbr> 1200<abbr>l.</abbr> and more, <hi>per annum,</hi> beſides all the bribes they get, and the falſe Accounts they make; So that in this life, the rich have their pleaſures, but poore <hi>Lazarus</hi> paines.</p>
            <p>Seeing the Parliament ordained, that none ſhould be accepted to be a Parliament-man, that had been a Monopolizer to the Kings Counſell, and falſe Judges againſt the Liberties of the free-men of <hi>England,</hi> is it not as unjuſt to imploy any man in a place of Truſt, Credit, or profit now in Parliament time, that have been known to be a Monopolizer in any place or Office to or for the Parliament, to the prejudice of the Free-men of <hi>England?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Further it was omitted in the former part of this book, where complaint is made both of injuſtice to well-doers, and no juſtice to evill doers, that (according to the Parliaments booke of Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, pag. 259. and 260.) <hi>Whoſoever ſhall ſerve or aſſiſt the King in theſe
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:113245:25"/>
Warres, are Traytors by the fundamentall Lawes of this Kingdome, and have been ſo adjudged by two Acts of Parliament.</hi> 11. <hi>Richard</hi> 2. 1. <hi>Hen.</hi> 4.</p>
            <p>And pag. 576. of the ſaid book, <hi>It is declared by the Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons aſſembled in Parliament, that whereas the King, ſeduced by wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Counſell, doth make warre againſt his Parliament and People, and for the promoting of that war, divers forces both of horſe and foot have been, and are leavied and raiſed by ſeverall perſons, and his Majeſties good Subjects are moſt cruelly robbed, ſpoiled and ſlaine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>To the end that no man may be miſled through ignorance, the Lords and Commons in Parliament declare, that all ſuch perſons as ſhall upon any pretence whatſoever, aſſiſt his Majeſtie in this warre with Horſe, Armes, Plate or money, are Traytors to his Majeſtie, the Parliament, and the Kingdome, and ſhall be brought to condigne puniſhment for ſo high an offence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yea, and according to the book of Articles for Warre, <hi>pag. It is enacted to be death unto any whoſoever, who holdeth Intelligence and correſpondency with the enemy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All which Sir <hi>John Lenthall,</hi> and the Speaker his Brother have done, and yet it muſt neither be proved againſt them, nor they try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed nor arraigned, but altogether excuſed, cleered, and freed, even by Vote of Parliament, and the accuſers both priſoned and arraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for them; yea, &amp; a Committe choſen to deviſe and inflict puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments againſt the Accuſers, ſo that ſtill the juſt are condemned, and the wicked abſolved.</p>
            <p>Pſal. 9.18, 19. <hi>For the needy ſhall not alway be forgotten: the expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation of the poore ſhall not periſh for ever: Ariſe, O Lord, let not man prevail, let the Heathen be judged in thy ſight.</hi> And 12.5. <hi>For the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of the poor, for the ſighing of the needy, now</hi> will I ariſe, <hi>ſaith the LORD, I will ſet him in ſafety, from him that puffeth at him.</hi> And 35.10. <hi>All my bones ſhall ſay, LORD, who is like unto thee! which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livereth the poore from him that is too ſtrong for him yea, the poore and the needy from him that ſpoileth him?</hi> And 37.14. <hi>The wicked have drawne out the ſword, and have bent their bow, to caſt downe the poor and needy, and to ſtay ſuch as be of upright converſation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And 62.9, 10. <hi>Surely men of low degree are vanity, and men of high degree are a lie, to be laid in the ballance, they are altogether lighter then vanity. Truſt not in oppreſſion, become not vaine in robbery; if riches in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:113245:25"/>
ſet not your hearts upon them.</hi> And 74.19. <hi>O deliver not the ſoul of thy Turtle Dove, unto the multitude of the wicked, forget not the Congregation of thy poore for ever.</hi> And 82.3, 4, 5. <hi>Defend the poore and fatherleſſe, doe juſtice to the afflicted and needy. Deliver the poore and needy, rid them out of the band of the wicked, they know not, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will they underſtand: they walk on in darkneſſe, all the foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the earth are out of courſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And 92.6, 7. <hi>A bruitiſh man knoweth not, neither doth a fool under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand this; When the wicked ſpring as the graſſe, and when all the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of iniquity doe flouriſh, it is, that they ſhall be deſtroyed for ever.</hi> And 118.8.9. <hi>It is better to truſt in the Lord, then to put confidence in man. It is better to truſt in the Lord, then to put confidence in Princes.</hi> And 146.3. <hi>Put not your truſt in Princes, nor in the ſonne of man, in whom there is no helpe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Iſaiah. 10.1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6. <hi>Woe unto them that decree unrighteous de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees, and write grievous things, which they have preſcribed. To turn aſide the need, from judgement, and to take away the right from the poor of my people, that Widdows may be their prey, and that they may robbe the fatherleſſe. And what will ye doe in the day of Viſitation: and in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation which ſhall come from farre? to whom will ye ſeek for help? and where will ye leave your glory? Without me they ſhall bow down under the Priſoners, and they ſhall fall under the ſlaine, for all this his anger is not turned away, but his hand is ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>retched out ſtill. O Aſſyrian, the rod of mine anger, and the ſtaffe in their hand is mine indignation. I will ſend him againſt an hypocriticall Nation; and againſt the people of my wrath, I will give him a charge to take the ſpoile, and to take the prey, and to tread them downe like the myre in the ſtreets.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>The chiefe faults eſcaped in the printing, either through the Authours abſence, or the Correctours negligence.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>In page 4. l. 22. read <hi>the laſt but one of.</hi> p. 5. l. 2. read <hi>and that.</hi> &amp; l. 7. read <hi>for the ſame.</hi> p. 7. l. 37. r. <hi>and juſtly</hi> for <hi>hence juſtly.</hi> and read <hi>may condemne</hi> for <hi>may not condemne.</hi> p. 9. l. 20. r. <hi>of which you may.</hi> and l. 32. r. <hi>are culpable.</hi> p. 10. l. 19. r. <hi>publick</hi> for <hi>bublick<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> p. 15. l. 18. r. <hi>that call evill good, and good evill.</hi> and adde to the next
<pb facs="tcp:113245:26"/>
line, <hi>Job</hi> 14.4. Who can bring a clean thing out of an uncleane? not one. read 25.4. and <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 51.5. p. 16. l. 16. r. <hi>to priſon without cauſe ſhewed.</hi> and l. 18. r. <hi>to force him to commit a crime.</hi> &amp; l. 26. r. <hi>and then make</hi> for <hi>and then to make</hi> p. 17. l. 14. r. ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>for</hi> ſtreightned, l. p. 37. l. 18. r. ſuites <hi>for</hi> ſuite, p. 39. l. 1. r. according to thoſe, <hi>for,</hi> according thoſe. p. 40. l. 23. r. conſider, <hi>for</hi> cnſider. p. 43. l. 16. r. If there were, <hi>for,</hi> Is there.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>THE POSTSCRIPT, Containing divers ſentences belonging to ſeverall paſſages of this Book, which were in their due places omitted, and here at laſt remembred.</head>
            <p>ADde to page <hi>16.</hi> l. <hi>29.</hi> So that firſt, he was committed by Order and Vote of Parliament, without cauſe ſhewed, and then ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, for refuſing to anſwer upon Interrogatories to their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee of Examinations; which is contrary, <hi>1.</hi> To the Great Charter of <hi>England. 2.</hi> To the very words of the <hi>Petition of Right. 3.</hi> To the act made this preſent Parliament, for aboliſhing the <hi>Star-chamber, 4.</hi> To the ſolemne Oath and Proteſtation of this Kingdome. <hi>5.</hi> To the great Covenant and Solemne Vow, made upon paine of eternall damnation, for uniting the two Kingdomes together. <hi>6.</hi> And moſt principally of all, contrary to the infallible Rules of Gods own moſt ſacred Word, which forbids that any man ſhould anſwer upon queſtions to accuſe, condemne, and conſequently to kill and deſtroy himſelf, or that any man ſhould be condemned before he be heard. And <hi>7.</hi> Contrary to all juſtice, equity, conſcience, ſenſe, reaſon, the very practiſe of the Romiſh Heathens, love, duty, brotherly affection, Chriſtianity, Reformation, Comiſeration, or Compaſſion. <hi>8.</hi> Contrary to the Kingdoms great truſt, committed by their grand Commiſſion to the Parliament, for defending and improving, and no wiſe for deſtroying nor diſannulling their Liberties, and ſo alwayes for the Weale, but never for the woe of the Free-men of <hi>England,</hi> other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe they are not only to be bidden<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> take heed to their injuſtice<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but to be called to an account, and cenſured accordingly.</p>
            <p>That in regard the Kingdome is in ſo pittifull and great diſtreſſe, and that the moſt and beſt things that ever this Parliament did, were firſt motioned by private men, and then authoriſed and eſtabliſhed by them; it would be excellent and needfull, if they would ordaine, that every free-man of <hi>England,</hi> who is able, would beſtow his ſervico one yeere at leaſt, freely for the good of the Civill State, in any Place or Office of Truſt, whereof his skill and breeding doe fit him, to be moſt capable, according as they ſhall be choſen, and thoſe who are not able to ſerve freely for a
<pb facs="tcp:113245:26"/>
yeere, and to have competent maintenance allowed unto them, to the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue of <hi>50.</hi> or <hi>60<abbr>l.</abbr>
               </hi> a yeere, according to their charge; if ſuch be choſen for their skill and diligence, though they want outward means: for which allowance, thoſe that are conſcienſcious, will doe as good ſervice, at leaſt, as ſome others, who have <hi>1000.</hi> or <hi>2000.</hi> a yeere.</p>
            <p>The like rule is no leſſe, but rather farre more excellent and needfull, to be obſerved and eſtabliſhed in matters concerning the Church-ſtate wherein her ſervants are to performe their duties freely, they being able to maintain themſelves, and thoſe with them, whether by means obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed formerly, or induſtry uſed daily; otherwiſe, to have the like allowance of <hi>50.</hi> or <hi>60<abbr>l.</abbr>
               </hi> a yeere, according to their charge.</p>
            <p>And that the remainder of all Church-living, obtained by the ſubtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Antichriſt, be n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>w wholly imployed to the ſupply of the Kingdomes manifold preſent neceſſities, and after the Warres are ended, to the pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Kingdoms great debts, contracted upon the publick faith.</p>
            <p>But if in caſe, that the Clergy or any of them ſhall not be content with the aforeſaid allowance, which is ſufficient for as honeſt men, that then it might be free for thoſe whom God ſhall be pleaſed to fit with ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent abilities to ſupply their places freely: to the intent, it may not be ſaid of them, as of the Scribes and Phariſees, that they ſhut up the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heaven, and will neither enter in themſelves, nor yet ſuffer thoſe that would. <hi>Matth. 23.13. Luk. 14.52.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Appendix of one of Mr. <hi>Prinnes</hi> bokes, authorized by the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, called <hi>The Soveraign power of Parliaments and Kingdoms,</hi> beginning at <hi>pag. 1.</hi> It is manifeſted by ſundry Hiſtories &amp; Authours, that in the ancient <hi>Roman</hi> Kingdome and Empire<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in the <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>German</hi> Empires, derived out of it, in the old <hi>Grecian, Indian, Egyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian</hi> Realmes, in the Kingdome of <hi>France, Spaine, Italy, Hungaria, Bohemia, Denmark, Poland, Swethland, Scotland,</hi> yea of <hi>Judah, Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> and others mentioned in the Scripture, the ſupreame Soveraignity and Power, reſided not in the Emperours and Kings themſelves, but in their Kingdomes, Senates, Parliaments, People, who had not onely power to reſtrain, but cenſure and remove their Emperours &amp; Princes, for their tyranny and miſ-government: Where alſo there is an anſwer to the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall Arguments to prove Kings above whole Kingdomes and Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and not queſtionable nor accountable to them, nor cenſurable by them for any exorbitant actions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The 4. page, 6. 7. 10. 11. 13. 17. 101. 112. 123. 125. 150. 151. 153. 154. 159.</hi> are moſt excellent for deciding thoſe differences, which I referre to the juditious and courteous Reader to peruſe at his leiſure.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>Printed</hi> Octob. 1645.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
